<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>wilkie writes a thing</title><description>wilkie's blog on tech and diversity</description><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com</link><item><title>OurCS</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/our-cs</link><description><![CDATA[<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/our-cs/our_cs_0_small.JPG' title='' alt='OurCS participants for 2013.' /><br /><div class='caption'>OurCS participants for 2013.</div></div><p></p>

<p>On October 18th, I spent the weekend leading a team of 4 undergraduate women in an exploration of distributed systems for collaboration. <a  href='http://www.cs.cmu.edu/ourcs/' title=''>OurCS</a>, which stands for <strong>O</strong>pportunities for <strong>U</strong>ndergraduate <strong>R</strong>esearch in <strong>C</strong>omputer <strong>S</strong>cience, held a workshop at <a  href='http://cmu.edu' title=''>CMU</a> with organizers also from the <a  href='http://pitt.edu' title=''>University of Pittsburgh</a> where researchers from many areas in or around computer science led a team of undergraduate women in order to exhibit the wide variety of topics one could study in this field. I was invited along with a dozen other researchers to lead a team through a tough technology problem.</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/our-cs/degrees.jpg' title='' alt='Computer Science suffers from a declining gender inclusivity.' /><br /><div class='caption'>Computer Science suffers from a declining gender inclusivity.</div></div><p></p>

<p>The motivation for the event is one that I would hope is rather well-known by now. If you aren&#39;t aware, however, the computer science field, and the tech industry at large, has a critical problem with diversity. There is an insurmountable amount of evidence, but for this discussion, I&#39;ll just point to the STEM field degree trends. Computer Science is the only STEM (That is, Science-Technology-Engineering-Mathematics) field with a dramatically negative trend in the gender ratio of the degrees awarded. This workshop is an example of one small event, that must be combined with many others, that serves as a possible <strong>solution</strong> to this incredible social problem.</p>
<h2 id='speakers'>Speakers</h2>
<p>The OurCS workshop combined both the active research and interactive component already alluded to, and also invited speakers to talk about their research or their roles in industry during scheduled downtime. There was a careful mix of industry, faculty, and graduate student speakers all giving their own perspective to being a woman in their respective areas.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>It’s a great experience for meeting other women in the field, as well as seeing the research they’re currently involved in -- for inspiration.
<div class="citation">&mdash; <cite>OurCS Participant</cite></div></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Although many of the research leaders mentioned that they wished they had more time in their groups, the speakers were still a necessary and important part of the workshop experience. These perspectives help to remove the stigma from the field causing non-men to reconsider computer science. Research has shown that much of both the disinterest and even the negative performance of those underrepresented in the field can be rooted to the development of these stereotypes. For a quick video about one particular study, I recommend <a  href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TYwI-qM20x4' title=''>Sapna Cheryan&#39;s</a> talk about her work.</p>
<h2 id='projects'>Projects</h2>
<p>I, for one, was most impressed (beyond the ability of the students) with the diversity of the <a  href='http://www.cs.cmu.edu/ourcs/Team_Leaders_and_Projects.html' title=''>projects</a> available at the workshop: everything from building web applications to analyzing ssl attacks to recognizing different patterns of drums in a track of music to developing technology for accessibility. The students were given the list of projects and leaders ahead of time and were able to choose which project they wished to work on. Groups of 4 to 5 were then assigned to each of the 13 projects.</p>

<p>Students then spent several 2-hour periods during the workshop with their research leaders discussing and developing the project. This workshop promotes a teacher/student ratio that one could never achieve in a typical classroom setting. In this case, 1 to 5 or 2 to 5, depending on the number of project leaders in the group. This allows a greater interactivity to the women participating, which will hopefully offset the typical effect of a large classroom setting of the <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome' title=''>impostor syndrome</a>. This negative effect is commonly seen in computer science classrooms where a large number of male students participating may create doubt in women that they belong or are as capable. Inheriting the benefit from other women-only spaces, the workshop setting suggests the truth: women are very capable, they do belong, and they belong just as much in the typical classroom they will go back to.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Fantastic experience! This workshop revitalized my interest in Computer Science...
<div class="citation">&mdash; <cite>OurCS Participant</cite></div></p>
</blockquote>

<p>At the end of the workshop, every student gives a small presentation as part of their team to all participants and leaders about the work they accomplished over the weekend. No team leaders are involved in the presentations, only the students. Just like any classroom setting, it is <strong>their</strong> work and they receive all accolades. They were able to portray the intent and direction of their work and, in some cases (particularly a controversial webapp), had to actively defend it against critical questioning.</p>

<p>I very much recommend having more such events. They inspire and promote leadership and education. The more diverse graduate students we can inspire, the more diverse our teachers will become, and thus the more diverse our field overall. If you would like to talk to the organizers of OurCS, <a  href='http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~cfrieze/' title=''>Carol Frieze</a> is the current chair for the event and wants to spawn more workshops across the world. I&#39;ll now devote the rest of this article to my first-hand experience as a team leader.</p>
<h2 id='perspective'>Perspective</h2>
<p>For my part, I (along with Daniel Mosse, Chair of Computer Science at U. Pitt) led a group of four (Rachel, Deeksha, Grishma, and Lucy) in a design of a new form of code sharing infrastructure to rival that of <a  href='http://github.com' title=''>GitHub</a>. I had the idea and most of the infrastructure written before the workshop so as to lead immediately to discussion. With a distributed system, much of the design is to fix the leaks in the dam, so to speak. That is, there is no such thing as a perfect system&mdash; you are most concerned with preventing the system from failing.</p>

<p>Therefore, the first two parts of the workshop were about distributed systems in general. We discussed the role and motivation of distributed systems over centralized ones and gave an example of each. Afterward, I posed a real-world example of a system that could be implemented either way (bus card scanners for public transportation) and the students were quick to apply their newfound skills in designing a system and criticizing its flaws or finding and then mitigating malicious attacks.</p>

<p>From there, I proposed the code sharing design. It is worth explaining a little bit. The motivation stems from <a  href='posts/apples' title=''>this article</a> which calls for a reduction of abstractions. The design of the systems comes from <a  href='posts/djehuty-technical' title=''>another article</a> and this <a  href='https://speakerdeck.com/wilkie/xomb-plus-djehuty-a-remix-os-for-computation-liberation' title=''>talk</a>.</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/our-cs/our_cs_1_small.JPG' title='' alt='Thinking about distributed systems through implementation' /><br /><div class='caption'>Thinking about distributed systems through implementation</div></div><p></p>

<p>Essentially, it is the reduction of code into as small of pieces as you can imagine. Each useful piece of code is given an <strong>interface</strong> (name, description of how to invoke, think function definition). Relationships among interfaces can be thought of as an object-oriented network, however in this system, a single entity does not know of the entire object-oriented graph. A single interface can be passed among many nodes in the system to be <em>discovered</em>. When a system knows of a name for a piece of code (let&#39;s say <code>sort</code> for example) it is now aware that there is some code to invoke that behavior, but it does not know how to do it. So it will ask for an <strong>implementation</strong> of that interface. This is some code that will perform the behavior implied by its name. Now, whenever <code>sort</code> is invoked, it will compute the result with that implementation. Systems can then pass around or even create new implementations as they wish. Multiple implementations are a good thing.</p>

<p>The students were quick to point out a flaw that some implementations may do the wrong thing, whether by bugs (human-error), corruption (network-error), hardware (machine-error) or maliciousness. So, we introduced a new component to our system: the <strong>specification</strong> which describes the behaviors all implementations should be beholden to. Now any node in the system can introduce a <em>rule</em>, for instance <em>&quot;All elements in the output should be greater than or equal to the previous element&quot;</em> which would only allow implementations of <code>sort</code> that produced an ascending list. When new loopholes are found, any person can introduce a new rule.</p>

<p>With the full system, we could then discuss the social ramifications of this system. This is a socially distributed system, much like Twitter, facebook, or even GitHub. It relies on the fact that most people use the system because of its benefits and that most people are cooperative. There was some philosophical discussion about the motivations of people using this system that was very productive in highlighting some of the attack vectors for our system model.</p>

<p>At the end of the workshop, the students generally agreed that this system is a valid and practical criticism of centralized solutions to code sharing such as GitHub. Unlike GitHub, which generally funnels good ideas into a pass-fail system guided by only a very few number of rather non-diverse people, this system allows anybody to have a say on the global state of code. Any one person, regardless of their position relative to the code they are writing, can contribute a new way of doing something. That new technique can propagate through the system and improve various programs on remote systems automatically. The maintainers of projects and contributors need not communicate directly, but do end up collaborating more often.</p>
<h2 id='experiment'>Experiment</h2>
<p>To investigate this system, we simply used it! With the proof of concept protocol implemented, I had each student play the role of a node in the system. They would each find some data they wished to visualize as a graph. They had their pick from several open data registries, such as the <a  href='https://nycopendata.socrata.com/' title=''>NYC Open Data</a> project. You can see the code and instructions they used <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/ourcs-plotter' title=''>here</a>.</p>

<p>Essentially, there was an <em>interface</em> for plotting, found <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/ourcs-plotter/blob/master/interface/data_plot.rb' title=''>here</a> in ruby. They were responsible for implementing that interface using <a  href='http://www.gnuplot.info/' title=''>gnuplot</a>. My own implementation can be found <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/ourcs-plotter/blob/master/implementation/data_plot/wilkie.rb' title=''>here</a>. They were eventually going to teach each other their implementations through the protocol. I had a program running on a server that would take each set of data and each plot implementation and draw a graph for each permutation as it discovered new implementations.</p>

<p>After they were finished, they used a program that implemented the protocol. This was actually the same code running on all machines, including the server I had running the plotter. We looked at how it was implemented and showed the sharing that the system was capable of by downloading the implementations of their fellow students. In the end, we could look at the eventual plots.</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/our-cs/our_cs_3_small.JPG' title='' alt='After their presentation: Rachel, Grishma, Deeksha, and Lucy.' /><br /><div class='caption'>After their presentation: Rachel, Grishma, Deeksha, and Lucy.</div></div><p></p>

<p>The students were very active in their discussion of the protocol and the system and quickly identified faults and possible problems. They were all pivotal in pushing the idea further and have greatly influenced any further work I may do in this space. It just goes to show that nobody should ever underestimate any student and that this workshop can and does promote confidence and the understanding to every student that they <strong>do</strong> belong and their opinions and thoughts <strong>are</strong> valuable. Such a great experience.</p>

<p>For instance, the students independently determined that this system could use a distributed reputation system to mitigate actively malicious implementations and specifications. They have in fact added to the entire discourse of distributed systems in only a matter of hours!</p>

<p>So, to conclude, let&#39;s look at the result. The following five images (a subset chosen from the many permutations) show each of the students (and my original plotter) plot implementations working on Grishma&#39;s dataset. As you can see, Grishma&#39;s original plot is at the top and it is drastically different from the other students. However, by allowing for this type of collaborative code sharing system, she can now see other ideas and be inspired by other techniques. For instance, the bottom chart, which shows a stacked bar graph, may better represent her data. This demonstrates that the system can indeed allow collaboration without explicit human arbitration, and that this is valuable. Now, we can go on to producing a larger system that will extend this idea to all code!</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/our-cs/grishma_5.gif' title='' alt='!' /></div><p>
</p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/our-cs/grishma_1.gif' title='' alt='!' /></div><p>
</p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/our-cs/grishma_3.gif' title='' alt='!' /></div><p>
</p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/our-cs/grishma_7.gif' title='' alt='!' /></div><p>
</p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/our-cs/grishma_9.gif' title='' alt='!' /></div><p></p>
]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/our-cs</guid></item><item><title>The Zed Shaw Phenomenon</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/the-zed-shaw-phenomenon</link><description><![CDATA[<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/the-zed-shaw-phenomenon/zedshaw.png' title='' alt='If you email me, please give me your best shot at describing what a crazy ass tweaker is.' /><br /><div class='caption'>If you email me, please give me your best shot at describing what a crazy ass tweaker is.</div></div><p></p>

<p>Goodness. The tech world must be really unfriendly, or alternatively I must be the absolute scum of the planet. Let&#39;s figure out what I did.</p>
<h2 id='indirection_is_not_abstraction'>Indirection Is Not Abstraction</h2>
<p>Back in December of 2012, <a  href='http://twitter.com/zedshaw' title=''>Zed Shaw</a> wrote an essay entitled <a  href='http://zedshaw.com/essays/indirection_is_not_abstraction.html' title=''>Indirection Is Not Abstraction</a> (if link is <a  href='/shaw_indirection.txt' title=''>broken</a>). In this, Shaw notes that there are a few misconceptions about the definitions of several terms used to describe methods of modular design and code isolation: interfaces, abstractions, and indirection. Basically, he suggests that our fellow coders and engineers mix them up and conflate them with other concepts.</p>

<p>The article is clearly a bit of a work in progress, as noted by Shaw himself in the concluding paragraph. It is not particularly well-written or well-structured. Shaw uses a writing style that conjures this image of the ever irritating shock-jock. If there is something he doesn&#39;t like, he emphasizes with expletives. If there is <em>someone</em> he doesn&#39;t like, he will go out of his way to find the room to take a shot at them. For instance, later on, Zed Shaw manages to inexplicably slip in a link to a search for <em>&quot;Dave Winer Asshole.&quot;</em></p>

<blockquote>
<p>It’s even worse
when the implementer realizes that if he implements the most complicated piece
of shit possible then he can go rogue consultant and make tons of mad cash
helping poor unsuspecting companies implement his steaming pile of bullshit.
Harsh words? You bet. But I’m fed up with people imposing their faulty
definitions and ideas on me without any way for me to easily fight back with a
reasonable explanation as to why their crap is steaming.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This writing style is difficult to parse and makes the reader wonder how concise the article could be if such filler was removed. For instance, the paragraph above provides the motivation for the piece. You might believe, only knowing the intent of the article, that the motivation would be to provide a better structure for discussing modular design. However, Zed Shaw&#39;s stream of consciousness relays a motivation to provide a better means for him to tell you (male implementors, not women apparently) that your code is similar to excrement wasting away in the sunlight.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>An unbelievable 6 levels of indirection just to add a fucking object to a fucking collection. This is the kind of bullshit that chaps my ass purple and makes me want to eat babies.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>...and to prevent him from desiring the consumption of small children in this unbelievably lazy reference found later on. Sigh. People. Look. This isn&#39;t hard. Killing a baby is not a valid literary device. It does not invoke peaceful idyllic imagery that helps you make your point through nostalgia. Stop it.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, Zed Shaw hits some good points and gives some decent ideas about how to better describe what an abstraction is. Of course, this is done in a paragraph that was probably supposed to be a bulleted list because it has a bunch of random asterisks between each sentence, but, as I said, the content in that mess is actually very good. (Hint: he doesn&#39;t swear or talk about the color of his butt.)</p>
<h2 id='commenting_on_abstractions'>Commenting on Abstractions</h2>
<p>Now let us focus on how I am involved. I research distributed systems and operating design. The whole indirection, interfaces, and abstractions thing? I&#39;ll let you in on a secret... That&#39;s what an operating system is. Therefore, I saw the gaps in an unfinished article and figured I had something useful to say. I gave the following post of my own in response to his article on <a  href='https://lobste.rs/s/ja5ihv/indirection_is_not_abstraction/comments/nl5sy4' title=''>lobste.rs</a>:</p>

<p><em>&quot;I had no idea the terms were so misused! It’s pretty simple, though. You have interfaces… if the implementations change behind them, that doesn’t mean your interface is flexible. It just means you have essentially a commit history that the interface allows you to ignore. Therefore, interfaces are not abstractions. Java misuses the term ‘abstract,’ because their usage only has meaning at the language parse time where it implies the lack of implementation logic. However, at runtime, an abstract class does not provide an abstraction, but an interface. However, we conflate the term with the notion of usage abstraction.</em></p>

<p><em>&quot;Zed does a terrible job at illustrating a true abstraction. Abstractions take away things. They simplify. They consolidate, perhaps, but they consolidate power through generalization. A programming language is an abstraction of a machine language. A machine language is an interface to the CPU’s control and arithmetic units. A machine language doesn’t abstract because it doesn’t limit.</em></p>

<p><em>&quot;I’ll add that abstractions are generally not machine-driven. They are people-driven. We abstract because some interfaces are too complicated. We abstract with natural language. We want things to be easier for the sake of programmers. A programming language is an abstraction because ‘var i = j + 1’ is so much better than the machine equivalent, however we sacrifice something to do this. That’s generally a good test for determining which something is. API’s are interfaces (yes, duh), Frameworks/languages are abstractions (read as: should be)</em></p>

<p><em>&quot;Zed doesn’t really talk about where the discrepancy comes from (because people are dumb isn’t really good enough.) What really gets people is that interfaces usually have implementations which make use of abstractions. So, this is also a question of scoping. An implementation can make use of an abstraction, however, an interface cannot force the usage of an abstraction (since an interface is just a name and a behavior.) A test for that is whether or not the implementation can eschew the abstraction by reinventing the universe to provide equivalent behavior. But looking at the wrong scope when you design can certainly lead to this problem of term discrepancy.&quot;</em></p>
<h2 id='zed_shaw_responds'>Zed Shaw Responds</h2>
<p>Apparently the post was well-received enough to catch Zed Shaw&#39;s attention, which I suppose was my first mistake.</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/the-zed-shaw-phenomenon/zedshaw_3.png' title='' alt='!zedshaw' /></div><p></p>

<p>Zed Shaw&#39;s response was not a very friendly one. He stripped my handle out of the reply to Steve and gives that common criticism of criticism: <em>&quot;you didn&#39;t even read it.&quot;</em> Steve did that thing that your friends do when you are out with them and they run into some Cool People, and he started to distance himself from me like it was coincidence that I was in the same room. That was disappointing, but I agree with Steve&#39;s careful implication that it is a bit confusing that I could both repeat what Shaw said and yet in the same small post also suggest that he was wrong.</p>

<p>It felt very odd to see this conversation unfold with me as the topic without either giving me an opportunity to contribute. <strong>I felt a bit restrained as I didn&#39;t seem to have the authority to defend myself</strong>. Yet, overall I didn&#39;t particularly care. <em>&quot;Oh well,&quot;</em> I thought, <em>&quot;I got my Zed-Shaw-Hates-You-Achievement. 10 Points.&quot;</em> The thing is, the comment I posted is very on point, which is all that matters when you write. You always anger somebody with your research. There is this expression people like to console you with resembling <em>&quot;if you make people angry, you&#39;re doing something right.&quot;</em> But, in reality, some people are just really touchy when you are working on a similar project. I&#39;m not sure if it is fear, or related to what territorial dogs do in the park, but it happens.</p>

<p>The important part is that my post is not wrong and I stand by it. The idea that interfaces should be considered first-class over abstractions because abstractions are always summarizations of a set of interfaces is an important idea. One that I believe Zed Shaw didn&#39;t really care about, so I made instead. But what if it wasn&#39;t me and it was somebody else? There must be others that are completely suppressed by this behavior.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Feel free to contact me with comments on this essay. It is still being worked on and is open for review. I’m pretty sure it makes no sense right now, but the major points should be there. I’m especially interested if you have any examples which you find relevant to the discussion, either for or against what I’m saying.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the end, I have to say; I was scratching my head a bit by his reaction. If he suggests himself that the post makes no sense and that he invites comments including criticism, why was my post so ill-received?</p>
<h2 id='the_bully_mindset'>The Bully Mindset</h2>
<p>Zed Shaw insists that I said he is wrong. I did no such thing. I agreed with many of his points. However, if I squint my eyes, I think I can see where that sentiment is coming from: <em>&quot;Zed does a terrible job at illustrating a true abstraction.&quot;</em></p>

<p>Why would I use the word <em>terrible</em> ? Because it is true. But I&#39;m not calling him wrong, rather I&#39;m suggesting that the writing quality is poor, because it is. It was an incredible eyesore for one. Also, he illustrates many examples of awful, tedious object hierarchies and gives some decent definitions of the terms, yet, he does not give any examples of what in the real-world actually abides by those definitions. Therefore, I did. I felt that this was the weakest part of the work, and I described it as such.</p>

<p>So wait. Could it be, then, that Zed Shaw is offended by the word <em>terrible</em> ? Could it be that the same person who desires a means to call your code a pile of feces shrieks at such a negative adjective?</p>

<p>Let&#39;s catch up to the present. How did this come back up almost 8 months later? Recently Zed Shaw published an <a  href='http://xoratelier.com/' title=''>idea</a> where people would pay him to work on his projects. Kurtis Rainbolt Greene offered reasonable criticism of the structure of the program. In reply, Zed Shaw spouts a stream of expletives about how absurd Kurtis apparently is to him.</p>

<p>In frustration, Kurtis issues a status about how Zed Shaw attacked rather than reasoned, and I felt the need to express solidarity. This is very much my experience from before where criticism was met with immediate aggression. I tagged Zed&#39;s handle (something he didn&#39;t afford me.) When Zed replied to me, shocked that I would be so brazen, I pointed out the tweet where he had attacked my post while dropping my handle and then... well, head back to the top of this page. He blew up.</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/the-zed-shaw-phenomenon/zedshaw_5.png' title='' alt='For the record, I've indeed secured funding for students to work on my projects. They were paid a monthly stipend and they acquired attribution and references for their work. It is not only possible to pay undergraduate students through grants, it's as common as it is necessary. But that's a different argument for a different day.' /><br /><div class='caption'>For the record, I've indeed secured funding for students to work on my projects. They were paid a monthly stipend and they acquired attribution and references for their work. It is not only possible to pay undergraduate students through grants, it's as common as it is necessary. But that's a different argument for a different day.</div></div><p></p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/the-zed-shaw-phenomenon/zedshaw_2.png' title='' alt='The Internet is a magical place where pointing out somebody being a jerk toward you is actually you being mean to them.' /><br /><div class='caption'>The Internet is a magical place where pointing out somebody being a jerk toward you is actually you being mean to them.</div></div><p></p>
<h2 id='open_source_bullies'>Open-Source Bullies</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>@wilkieii The thing you&#39;re leaving out is I&#39;m mean to people like you and KRG who shit on me but think I&#39;m supposed to be nice in reply.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Let&#39;s get to the real point, here: <strong>this is the type of personality that you can readily find within the tech community</strong>. One that believes they have authority and dominion of their opinion of you, but not the other way around. A proud individual who believes they are smarter than you, threatened by you if you start to prove otherwise.</p>

<p>These people hurt our communities. They lurk in <a  href='http://cdm266901.cdmhost.com/utils/getfile/collection/p266901coll4/id/655/filename/617.pdf' title=''>IRC channels</a> waiting to <a  href='http://code-worrier.com/blog/why-rtfm-is-some-bullshit/' title=''>harass new programmers</a>. These are the types of people who discourage women from participating in <a  href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TYwI-qM20x4' title=''>classrooms</a> and within our <a  href='http://marc.info/?l=linux-kernel&m=137391401112514&w=2' title=''>open source communities</a>. These high-and-mighty types that only desire to proclaim their superiority and describe to you the exact composition of your inferiority, even if you are merely trying to learn.</p>

<p>They have thousands of twitter followers, heavily influencing the culture. They control our <a  href='http://www.wired.com/wiredenterprise/2012/06/torvalds-nvidia-linux/' title=''>systems</a> and make decisions that influence everything we do with computers and networks. Linus controls Linux, the basic software that is executed and makes decisions for our applications, and he has racked up <a  href='http://archive09.linux.com/articles/114231' title=''>quite</a> a <a  href='https://lkml.org/lkml/2012/12/23/75' title=''>list</a> of <a  href='http://marc.info/?l=linux-kernel&m=137391401112514&w=2' title=''>offenses</a>. Zed Shaw writes web server code, the basic software that many use to respond to requests from people who use our applications. As a queer, operating system and kernel developer, <strong>the thought of these bullish types having control where diversity should reign is a very scary thought</strong>.</p>

<p><em>&quot;Read the Fucking Manual,&quot;</em> they will say. (They like to swear, don&#39;t they?) They will use their established influence to scare even the likes of Steve Klabnik into being a bit more passive. I mean, you don&#39;t want to hurt your chances of being one of the Cool People, right? You don&#39;t want to be seen as the aggressive one. That is, other prominent individuals are not pushing back for the rest of us. <em>&quot;Grow some thicker skin,&quot;</em> they will paraphrase in retort to every accusation. These bullies, such as Shaw, will use their environment to their advantage and make it look like you are in the bad, instead of them.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/the-zed-shaw-phenomenon/zedshaw_4.png' title='' alt='!zedshaw' /></div><p></p>

<p>They are the type of people who like to get the last word.</p>
<h2 id='the_truth'>The Truth</h2>
<p>To conclude, we have to come together and accept the truth: <strong>the tech community is an extremely unfriendly place</strong>. We cannot placate such incidents as they hurt our ability to teach and collaborate and thus hinder our progress. It might be <a  href='http://ashedryden.com/blog/the-risk-in-speaking-up' title=''>hard</a>, but let&#39;s make sure we take a stand. Let&#39;s <a  href='http://ashedryden.com/blog/increasing-diversity-at-your-conference' title=''>create</a> a safer space for people to learn. Let&#39;s claim the last word for ourselves, and say, <strong><em>&quot;We can do better without you.&quot;</em></strong></p>
]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/the-zed-shaw-phenomenon</guid></item><item><title>Reuleaux Selectors</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/reuleaux-selectors</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Whether you believe gender follows essentialist principles or is constructed, the concept of gender identity is a very complicated subject.
Contrary to unfortunately popular belief, gender is not chosen from a binary as though it were conjured at the whim of a coin-toss.
Gender is different for just about every individual and as infinite as our collective imaginations can bear.</p>

<p>In this post, we describe a new form of gender selection interface (the <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/blog/blob/master/public/javascript/reuleaux-selectors/reuleaux-selectors.js' title=''>code</a> is open and in need of refactoring).
It is worth noting this disclaimer: we are not trying to develop the perfect representation.
For decades, the computer science community has not explored new approaches to this problem, and thus for decades people have been excluded based on not being able to fully reflect themselves.
There are a few reasons why&mdash; particularly computer science&#39;s predilection toward metrics and peer-review which hurt divisive, intentionally vague, or exploratory work.
Yet this is exactly meant to be a provocative push to get people, including UI/UX researchers, invigorated about this problem.
We should ultimately be collaborating on a better solution.</p>

<p>For now, though, if you ask for gender, reconsider asking.
If that fails, consider asking for pronouns instead.
If you still can&#39;t say no, use a text field.</p>
<h2 id='what_is_gender_'>What is gender?</h2>
<p>In order to describe a method of how to represent gender and allow an individual to select a gender identity, we first will explore the variety of gender we tend to describe, and the variety of gender that exists.
Many people will be surprised at the amazing rainbow-like diversity of gender that the universe contains.
It is perfectly acceptable to be unaware, but as we build social spaces and as we interact with a diversity of people, we should certainly make an attempt to empathize.</p>
<h3 id='gender_binary'>Gender binary</h3>
<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/gender-binary.png' title='' alt='The gender binary is enforced by culture' /><br /><div class='caption'>The gender binary is enforced by culture</div></div><p></p>

<p>The prevailing, yet optimistically evolving, perspective of gender throughout society remains mostly that of a binary.
You are either a man or a woman and if you are not one of those two, you are pushed into situations where you have to choose. Our social networks, dating services, and other online communities should not enforce this broad and unfair generalization.</p>

<p>It is clear that our overall society enforces this concept through its presentation in various societal forms: which bathroom we use, and reinforced through cultural symbols: such as the ones that adorn such bathroom doors and through gendered language such as binary pronouns (he, she) and gendered nouns (blond, blonde in English).</p>

<p>There is no room for diversity here. A person could be on that fuzzy (and ever-changing) line between men and women. What pronouns do we use? Well, we should use what pronouns they prefer, and should ask for such. As it stands, though, we are still pushing this individual to select between two choices, when in fact, they may prefer another option. This choice is perfectly, and naturally, acceptable.</p>
<h3 id='gender_scale'>Gender scale</h3>
<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/gender-scale.png' title='' alt='The gender scale allows for bigender/intersex individuals, but not agender' /><br /><div class='caption'>The gender scale allows for bigender/intersex individuals, but not agender</div></div><p></p>

<p>Given that a binary system is inadequate for individuals not self-identifying at extremes, another option that people have presented to define gender is a sliding scale with male at one end and female at the other. This is better, because we can now represent more feminine men, masculine women, intersex, bigender, and some androgynous people. However, this scale actually still supports the concept of gender binary, and as such does not respect individuals that exist outside of its normative bounds. For instance, where does one go in the scale that have no self-identifiable gender characteristics? Frankly, an individual that is neither man nor woman is not necessarily in the middle of one particular scale.</p>
<h3 id='gender_spectrum'>Gender spectrum</h3>
<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/gender-spectrum.png' title='' alt='The gender spectrum is a continuum that allows for a variety of genders and allows for a diversity of non-conformity' /><br /><div class='caption'>The gender spectrum is a continuum that allows for a variety of genders and allows for a diversity of non-conformity</div></div><p></p>

<p>The reason gender is so hard to define as an input method is that, in reality, gender is more of a spectrum of possibility. Male and female are not truly endpoints, but rather simply points in the spectrum.</p>

<p>So, to interpret the spectrum as I have defined it in the image above, we would have male and female on opposite sides of a ring. Starting from female, moving around toward the northwest portion would add male identity and going toward the southeast portion would subtract female identity. Hitting the top-left would give you both gender identities and hitting the bottom-right would be void of both. By no means is this the only proper representation.</p>

<p>We could stop right here and say, &quot;let&#39;s use the spectrum above.&quot; While it does illustrate the idea that in reality gender has no endpoints, it is also a bit problematic about where certain representations are.
Agender individuals, represented here as &#9898;, are within the broad spectrum of gender options. However, you should be able to move from bigender, &#9893;, to agender without having to pass through male or female.</p>

<p>That is, it is good for representing the qualification of gender, but not very good for comparison.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/gender-triangle.png' title='' alt='The gender triangle represents the spectrum yet allows the middle point of agender to be the farthest point from any extreme' /><br /><div class='caption'>The gender triangle represents the spectrum yet allows the middle point of agender to be the farthest point from any extreme</div></div><p></p>

<p>Therefore, a triangle would represent the same idea. It does make certain landmarks clear by placing familiar gender identities in the corners. However, this should help individuals choose by selecting a gender identity relative to those landmarks.
Also, by placing agender at the midpoint, bigender at the bottom center, and polygender at the top, eschewing gender is always a matter of going toward the center without having to move through genders to be rid of them.</p>

<p>This representation is a 2d input that provides input for a three dimensional point. The point will be calculated as a vector of the distances to each corner. From there, we can create a gender selector by refining this triangle concept such that a fuller representation of the spectrum is available.</p>
<h2 id='defining_a_comparable_gender_value'>Defining a comparable gender value</h2><h3 id='triangles'>Triangles</h3>
<p>The intuitive attempt to represent directional values for male, female, and androgynous would be to use a triangle and place each gender at a corner.
This posed some difficulty in selection.
Based on informal feedback, some individuals were quick to place their marker in a corner directly.
The corners, by being corners, could not capture the fluidity of the spectrum.</p>

<p>Therefore, the corners should be rounded off in a way that did not compromise their position as an extent, but also give the impression of fluidity.</p>

<p>Another design flaw of the triangles is that the relationship between two extremes is a straight line. Although the straight line seems intuitive, the relationship to the center point changes rapidly across such a line. That is, one might believe that the relationship between two gender identities could go through the center point, yet that is not true. Individuals may misjudge the relative nature of two points as a result.</p>

<p>Related, the last design flaw of the triangle is that the center point is nearly invisible and hard to select. Since it represents agender, it seems fitting that the center point be expanded such that defining a point there would position the selector&#39;s knob outside of the bounds of the shape representing a value of gender.</p>

<p>Therefore, the triangle was abandoned.</p>
<h3 id='reuleaux_triangles'>Reuleaux triangles</h3>
<p>To revise the triangle to better reflect the gender spectrum, we expanded the center point to better accommodate agender qualities.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/gender-reuleaux.png' title='' alt='The Reuleaux ring is the result of considering better representations and visibility for agender/asexual individuals' /><br /><div class='caption'>The Reuleaux ring is the result of considering better representations and visibility for agender/asexual individuals</div></div><p></p>

<p>When you take a triangle and blow out its center point, you produce an interesting piece of geometry. It is essentially a three-sided ring defined by two similar <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reuleaux_triangle' title=''>Reuleaux triangles</a>.</p>

<p>Geometry time! A <strong>Reuleaux triangle</strong> is a three-sided curved polygon with a constant width along any line perpendicular to the tangent of the curve. It is produced by the arcs of three congruent circles with each circle&#39;s center point corresponding to a corner point of the triangle.</p>

<p></p>

<div class="image">
  <div id="genderTriFieldIllustration" style="width: 430px"></div>
  <input type="hidden" id="genderValI" value=""></input>
  <input type="hidden" id="genderXPosI" value=""></input>
  <input type="hidden" id="genderYPosI" value=""></input>
  <div class="caption">
    <strong>Interactive</strong>: Reuleaux coordinates are transformed into triangle coordinates.
  </div>
</div>

<p>In order to represent the data in a way that is intuitive, we transform the point the user selects within the Reuleaux to the corresponding point on a triangle. Drag the selector above to get a feel as to how the geometry relates. Notice that as you drag the selector along a curve, it corresponds to a line on the triangle. Also, every point along the boundary of the inner Reuleaux corresponds equally to the center point of the triangle.</p>
<h2 id='input_methods_we_have_now'>Input methods we have now</h2>
<p>Even though we have a growing awareness of the incorrectness of the notion of a gender binary, the presentation of only two choices is retained in our software systems and social networks.
The selection is given as a strict choice normally between two different values: male or female.</p>
<h3 id='dropdown'>dropdown</h3>
<p>The dropdown is the traditional gender selector. Generally, it seems developers tend to only allot the two familiar choices. Even social services proud to be used by millions of people, such as facebook, have long fought offering any amount of choice, even under <a  href='http://www.zdnet.com/blog/facebook/nepal-asks-facebook-for-third-sex-option/11117' title=''>heavy criticism</a>. Interestingly, facebook has always contained internal support for a third gender that users were <a  href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rb68sPtblyo' title=''>able to enable through a hack</a> which then used non-gendered pronouns to refer to them to friends.</p>

<p>Eventually, <a  href='http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/headlines/2014/02/heres-a-list-of-58-gender-options-for-facebook-users/' title=''>facebook added</a> a curated list of gender options, most of which are just variants along the cis/trans binary and vague angrogynous terms.
Notably, facebook hid their list of acceptable genders and employed in place of a drop-down an auto-complete text field, which is certainly an implicit drop-down.
However, with this change, they also ask for pronouns and allow people to select a long-supported non-gendered &#39;their&#39;.</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/fb_gender.png' title='' alt='Facebook, a social network with millions of users, allows basic non-binary genders if you can guess the terms they support.' /><br /><div class='caption'>Facebook, a social network with millions of users, allows basic non-binary genders if you can guess the terms they support.</div></div><p></p>

<p>There was a conscious effort of developers in general (facebook avoided this trend), perhaps to retrofit a proactive model with an existing system, to add a third catch-all option usually titled &quot;other.&quot;
This is an incorrect solution because culturally it paints the image that this third option represents a third gender, when it really collects those strictly outside of the cultural gender-binary.
It dismisses the gender identity of all of those outside male and female. Furthermore, the term &quot;<em>other</em>&quot; depicts these individuals as abnormal.
It says, you can be a man, a woman, or something else. This is not equality. This is merely placation without respect for identity.
Not to mention that some individuals may wish to opt out of the politics of gender and the &quot;other&quot; option unduly oppresses them into that system.</p>

<p>In the end, for a dropdown to be successful in representing the full spectrum of gender options, it would have to continue to add them as they become desired.
Such an exhaustive list would never-the-less be excluding somebody.
At the end of the day, the freedom to express one&#39;s gender identity could be better suited for an input method based upon the whole freedom-to-write-whatever mechanic.</p>
<h3 id='textfield'>textfield</h3>
<p>With that in mind, we need a way to depict gender that presents equal opportunity to all genders.
This is, of course, a simple textfield.
This solution is generally seen as a versatile solution that allows a wealth of choices.
It is a solution that is used, perhaps slightly strategically, by facebook&#39;s cultural competitor <a  href='http://www.sarahmei.com/blog/2010/11/26/disalienation/' title=''>Diaspora</a>.</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/diaspora-gender.png' title='' alt='The change to a text field for gender was a divisive issue for Diaspora, shown here, but not for Metafilter who originally had such a field for over 10 years. [1]' /><br /><div class='caption'>The change to a text field for gender was a divisive issue for Diaspora, shown here, but not for Metafilter who originally had such a field for over 10 years. [1]</div></div><p></p>

<p>However, it is not without fault. A textfield cannot describe all options because it is limited by language. It also does not represent degrees of gender. That is, one person can say &quot;male&quot;
and so can the next, yet, we cannot tell if such a set of individuals was presented with a scale, would they then say that they are 80% male and 70% male?
Does a textfield allow them to too quickly choose to pigeonhole themselves?</p>

<p>Also, a textfield is hard to compare. There are times when a genderqueer individual would like to use a more fluid value for gender identity in comparison to others. For instance, a dating
service. A textfield, beyond influencing self-pigeonholing, is difficult to quantify as a mathematical value. You could limit the choices to a tagged dropdown, <a  href='http://www.sarahdopp.com/blog/2010/designing-a-better-drop-down-menu-for-gender/' title=''>which has been proposed</a>,
however, you would then have to manually assign weights in order to determine how far away one gender is from another.</p>

<p>While the textfield is still invaluable and it is very apt to recommend it (perhaps in conjunction to our proposal), we need a field that can both provide a wealth of gender options that can represent the gender spectrum (qualification) <em>and</em> a field that produces values that can be easily compared with one another (quantification).</p>
<h2 id='the_selectors'>The selectors</h2>
<p>We believe the Reuleaux gender selector solves the issues apparent in other approaches. It provides a broad range of gender identities in a way that is fairly easy to use. Furthermore, it results in a quantifiable value, a three-dimensional coordinate, which can be used for comparison.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/gender-chart.png' title='' alt='The selector can identify a wide variety of genders independently giving freedom to the degree of strength of the identification.' /><br /><div class='caption'>The selector can identify a wide variety of genders independently giving freedom to the degree of strength of the identification.</div></div><p></p>
<h3 id='sexual_orientation_selector'>Sexual orientation selector</h3>
<p>One of the interesting extensions of the gender selector is also using it for sexual orientation.
This presents some issues and complications, but using the gender selector to also select for orientation works fairly well.
The one problem is that while gender is a union (I identify with male and female: I am bigender), sexual orientation tends to also be intersectional (I am attracted to those that are both male and female: I am attracted to bigenders).
That is, the selector allows you to put a point at the bottom of the field. But this indicates a union (bisexual) instead of somebody that happens to only be attracted to the specific bigender identity.</p>

<p></p>

<div class="image">
  <div style="width: 430px">
    <div id="genderTriField" style="float: left"></div>
    <input type="hidden" id="genderVal" value=""></input>
    <input type="hidden" id="genderXPos" value=""></input>
    <input type="hidden" id="genderYPos" value=""></input>
    <div id="sexualityTriFieldSimple"></div>
    <input type="hidden" id="sexualityValSimple" value=""></input>
    <input type="hidden" id="sexualityXPosSimple" value=""></input>
    <input type="hidden" id="sexualityYPosSimple" value=""></input>
  </div>
  <div class="caption">
    <strong>Interactive</strong>: Gender and orientation selectors as Reuleaux triangles.
  </div>
</div>

<p>This can be solved by allowing gender to be specified as a single point, and sexual orientation to be a set of points to form areas of selection.
In this form, if a gender identity that an individual <strong>A</strong> selects falls within the area given by the sexual orientation selector of person <strong>B</strong>, then you could say that <strong>A</strong> would be gender-compatible with <strong>B</strong> from <strong>B</strong>&#39;s perspective.
This greatly complicates the sexual orientation selector relative to the gender selector in terms of user ease of use.
However, in cases where this type of input is very useful (such as with dating services,) this complication can be tolerated by users in order to increase the quality of their representation.</p>

<p></p>

<div class="image">
  <div style="width: 430px">
    <div id="genderTriField2" style="float: left"></div>
    <input type="hidden" id="genderVal2" value=""></input>
    <input type="hidden" id="genderXPos2" value=""></input>
    <input type="hidden" id="genderYPos2" value=""></input>
    <div id="sexualityTriField"></div>
    <input type="hidden" id="sexualityVal" value=""></input>
    <input type="hidden" id="sexualityXPos" value=""></input>
    <input type="hidden" id="sexualityYPos" value=""></input>
  </div>
  <div class="caption">
    <strong>Interactive</strong>: Sexual orientation selector can select areas that indicate attraction to the given gender identity. Drag the middle circle out, use smaller circle to expand area. To remove a circle, shrink it until very small. As you drag circles out of the middle area, new circles can be added. Add as many as you would like.
  </div>
</div>

<p>Please experiment with the selectors above to create your identity profile below.</p>
<h3 id='describe_yourself'>Describe yourself</h3>
<p></p>

<div class="image">
  <div style="width: 470px">
    <div id="output">
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="caption">
    <strong>Interactive</strong>: Use the selectors directly above these to create your identity image.
  </div>
</div>
<h2 id='not_an_end_all_solution'>Not an end-all solution</h2><h3 id='genderfuck'>Genderfuck</h3>
<p>One of the issues with the gender identity selectors is that they represent a static, unchanging representation.
It could very well be that one&#39;s identity changes over time, perhaps even daily.
This selector would then have to be changed as the identity changes manually.</p>

<p>One solution would be to use an area selector for identity as well.
A genderfuck individual, whose identity is not well defined, can then select an area of identity.
Gender-compatibility can then be defined as whether or not the area of the gender identity intersects with the area of the sexual orientation, although this is not entirely perfect.</p>

<p>However, in the end, this selector is designed to only be effective for well-defined identities.
It is always best to include both this selector and a textfield for clarification.
The ability to well-define your identity is still the most practical and most awesome benefit to provide a user.</p>
<h3 id='physical_characteristics'>Physical characteristics</h3>
<p>This selector does not, in any way, take into account physical characteristics of the individual.
One criticism received for this selector is that one cannot specify clearly that they have a particular set
of genitalia. Also, as far as sexual gender preference goes, some were rather upset that they cannot specify
that they are attracted only to women with cisgendered reproductive systems.</p>

<p>After all is said and done, this selector is only concerned about gender. Physical characteristics do not correlate with gender identity, and therefore cannot be depicted in this selector.
That said, some interpret areas of the gender selector as indicating this, however.
Since no instruction was given, feedback in discussion shows that individuals do see a correlation that does not explicitly exist.
They may assign their gender identity accordingly, which is fine, and within the bounds of use of the selector.
However, you cannot reverse engineer that decision to draw any conclusions.</p>
<h3 id='ease_of_use'>Ease of use</h3>
<p>It is not clear how intuitive the selector is.
In open-trials, where no instruction is given, individuals were presented with the simple, single-point gender and sexuality selectors.
They were able to give feedback, privately and also among a forum.
I have suppressed the exact feedback due to privacy and due to the fact that the discussion was not fruitful (that is, sometimes a bit hateful) to the discussion on a whole.</p>

<p>However, it is difficult to conceive of a simpler way of inputting a broad range of gender choices.
It is possible that one could add the ability to use preset points according to a dropdown or determined from a textfield to prepopulate the selectors.
This would show the intention of the selectors and also help the assumed majority of people make quick decisions, but still allow the genderqueer community the ability to be visible by refining their identity further.</p>
<h2 id='general_advice_for_usage_of_gender_fields'>General advice for usage of gender fields</h2>
<p>If you add a gender field to your project, you must ask yourself the question: what do the users gain from being able to report this value?
The general advice that one can give is to drop it altogether, especially if there is nothing directly related to the service you are providing that benefits from gender.</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/gender-rdio.png' title='' alt='Imagine you are a person that does not fall cleanly into one of these two categories. You are now presented with a bright red flag that will not let you continue until you choose. How would you feel? (Image is rdio's registration and courtesy of @carols10cents)' /><br /><div class='caption'>Imagine you are a person that does not fall cleanly into one of these two categories. You are now presented with a bright red flag that will not let you continue until you choose. How would you feel? (Image is rdio's registration and courtesy of <a href="https://www.rstat.us/updates/50e8a221aeb89a00020202e4">@carols10cents</a>)</div></div><p></p>

<p>A common reason for including gender, even if only privately stored and never publicly displayed, is to provide humanization through gendered language, such as personalizing text with the correct pronouns.
If this is the case, then the correct action is to just simply ask the user for their preferred pronouns and allow for a non-gendered form if language permits (which <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender-neutral_pronoun#Summary' title=''>English does</a>).</p>

<p></p><div class='image border'><img src='/images/reuleaux-selectors/gender-rdio-response.png' title='' alt='Rdio only uses their gender information to provide linguistics. We recommend that pronouns be explicitly asked for in place of gender, and that you allow a non-gendered option (his/her/their.)' /><br /><div class='caption'>Rdio only uses their gender information to provide linguistics. We recommend that pronouns be explicitly asked for in place of gender, and that you allow a non-gendered option (his/her/their.)</div></div><p></p>

<p>When you are providing a social service, users may wish to publicly display their gender.
In these cases, since it directly benefits their ability to express their identity, you should allow for a free range of choice.
Therefore, in this case, simply use a textfield, and <strong>always</strong> allow them to specify nothing.
It may benefit to suggest common genders to allow more ease of use to the majority of normative users and to encourage genders that are quantifiable for statistical purposes.
However, you must look at this from your users&#39; perspective: which method improves <em>their</em> ability to <em>self</em>-describe <em>their</em> identity, because that&#39;s what <em>they</em> want.</p>

<p>As mentioned above, textfields may have some form of societal influence that actually could limit choice.
In this case, use the Reuleaux gender selector.
There is nothing that prevents you from using such a selector alongside a textfield.
This allows both a comparable value for gender and a way to self-label with a finer granularity (or for a user to make it very clear what gender they identify as.)</p>

<p>Such a combination seems most viable on a dating service that is genderqueer friendly where the matching logic is gender-seeking.
In such a case, it may offer better opportunities to suggest gender labels for the textfield based upon your gender value in the selector.
That is, using the gender value as a relevancy hint for the keyword search to order the suggestions more properly.</p>

<p>All in all, gender is a complicated subject.
It is best to avoid collecting that aspect of identity if possible.
However, we wish to make it clear that there is still room in social places where
gender is meaningful to also be willing to include individuals that fall outside of gender-normative groups.
We do not believe this is the end-all solution, but we do believe it is progress in a space that
lacks new ideas and it is our ultimate goal that it motivates discussion and even fresher solutions.</p>
<h3 id='references'>References</h3><ol><a id='ref_1'></a><li>Interesting statistics about textfield usage at Metafilter and relation to Diaspora&#39;s decision in Carina C. Zona&#39;s talk <a  href='http://confreaks.com/videos/1120-gogaruco2012-schemas-for-the-real-world' title=''>Schemas for the Real World</a>, 2012 Golden Gate Ruby Conference, exact reference is ~17:00.
</li></ol>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/reuleaux-selectors</guid></item><item><title>Stop Benchmarking Your Software Design</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/kaashoeks-law</link><description><![CDATA[<p>In our world, programmers look into producing better designs and software practices
in order to push progress. Researchers have generally accepted that we compare two designs by measuring
their relative performance. The metrics consist not only of the obvious time and space, but also power,
safety, and so on. In such cases, a new approach may come along for which programmers
can use, yet its authors only compare this new approach to priors and suggest it is &quot;faster&quot; by illustrating
some self-selected benchmarks. However, performance testing is not a viable metric to sufficiently show that
one interface or software design is better than another. It fact, it may dangerously dilute
our understanding of &quot;better&quot; by overestimating the absoluteness of any one result and
distracting us from other perhaps more important metrics unrelated to implementation performance.</p>
<h2 id='how_we_evaluate_operating_systems'>How we evaluate operating systems</h2>
<p>As a case study, systems researchers should note that operating systems do not optimize for the continuous redesign that all systems must
undergo to adapt to new advancements in hardware, which has to be almost instantaneously
exploited by the software using it. Furthermore, operating systems must also counter weaknesses
in the OS design that impact the software efficiency demanded by application developers.
That is, operating systems must continuously adapt, yet we do not evaluate their adaptability.</p>

<p>When we augment an operating system, we merely compare the result against the prior form by
running a suite of identical benchmarks against each system. We look for typical performance
benchmarks and any indication that bottlenecks, locks, and resources have been minimized.</p>

<p>However, this method of evaluation is meaningless in the grand scheme of the software system.
This process fails to control for the changing nature of systems as a whole. Operating systems
must change, and their ability to change must be higher than that of the rate of change of
hardware and the changing needs of people. An augmentation of a system that hinders this
rate of software change will only build an ineffective system around it.</p>
<h2 id='how_to_evaluate_operating_systems'>How to evaluate operating systems</h2>
<p>Because operating systems are in a constant state of flux, traditional performance metrics such as
response time, latency, power, and reliability represent only one particular way to evaluate such
systems. These metrics do not give definitive comparative information about how the design
underlying a particular OS competes against other software architectures. In order to quantify it,
we not only should look at these metrics, but must also acknowledge developer effort as a factor.</p>

<p>Developer effort is a measurement of the number of hours invested to achieve a given level of
runtime performance and the increase of performance of the piece of software. Consider adding
support for a new network card for two different operating systems. The cost to add support for
the hardware is different for each system depending on the OS design. Assuming that the final
performance of the driver, after tuning, will be the same, two options should be considered: a new
network driver, or adapting an existing network driver. If developer effort is too high, then it may
<em>not be cost effective to adapt a system</em>. In certain cases, developer effort may be so overwhelming
that it may be <strong>more</strong> cost effective to start from scratch.</p>
<h2 id='kaashoek__39_s_law'>Kaashoek&#39;s Law</h2>
<p>We propose to evaluate OS design by tuning two systems until they achieve the same level
of performance. In that case, the superior design is the one that required less developer effort.
We posit that level of achievable performance is a constant across system architectures, therefore
human effort is the only meaningful metric of comparison. To substantiate the above claim, we
note that recent work on operating systems has shown that it is futile to use traditional evaluation
approaches to make prescriptive statements about software architecture. For instance, despite
the concerns above, about multicore support in traditional OSes, given sufficient re-engineering
effort, Linux kernel limitations on scalability can be overcome [1]. We propose a generalization
of this finding, which we call <strong>Kaashoek’s Law</strong>*: the notion that given enough development time,
any piece of software can overcome a performance issue or feature deficit. To answer those who
attempt to differentiate operating systems not by performance but by feature set, we propose
<strong>Ganger’s Corollary</strong>&dagger;: anything you can do they can do; given enough time, they will do it.</p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, this concept has not been formally stated, however, evidence
abounds:</p>
<ul><li>In 2000, the SMPng project was launched as it became clear that FreeBSD’s SMP scalability was being hindered by a global kernel lock. As a part of this project, concluded in 2007, the
bottleneck was averted in most cases leading to improved performance through better scalability
[2].
</li><li>Microkernel design was much maligned due to the added overhead of context switching
for IPC. However, the L4 microkernel has progressed to the point where Wombat (Linux 2.6 on
L4) outperforms the Linux kernel on ARM due to fast address space switching [3].
</li><li>Extensible systems often use HTTPD performance to demonstrate advantages over a monolithic kernel.
However, [4] presents a compelling argument that good design and kernel optimizations in a
monolithic kernel can achieve the same HTTPD performance.
</li></ul>
<p>While it makes perfect sense to judge these techniques by their performance improvement,
this evaluation does not infer anything about the quality of the underlying OS design. Instead,
these techniques suggest that all systems are capable of providing the same level of performance.
Therefore, this asserts our position that the job of the OS designer is to <strong>minimize the amount of
developer effort necessary to provide these performance optimization techniques</strong>.</p>
<h2 id='modern_os_evaluation'>Modern OS Evaluation</h2>
<p>In our network driver case above, a typical research study would build the network driver on Linux
and compare with the prior driver. The study would control for environment by using the same machine
and thus exact hardware, but run two different Linux images where only the driver differs. Then the
researcher would run a benchmark suite that would run a gamut of popular networked applications
on a variety of workloads. The researcher would then highlight wins, losses, and ties and explain each
in the resulting paper.</p>

<p>Yet, if this driver was a result of new hardware, this research would not be able to conclude the
interference of the kernel abstractions. It may become the case that five years later, running the
same experiment using a newer version of Linux will allow the older driver to overcome the newer, or
produce a situation where an older idea can suddenly improve the researcher&#39;s driver.</p>

<p>More to the point, a new kernel design for a new operating system can never compare itself to something
established such as Linux. Over time, a new design can always overcome its flaws due to immaturity and
defeat an established work. This is Kaashoek&#39;s Law in work. Almost instantly, a researched work comparing
two operating systems will be invalidated. Only an ongoing comparison can ever be valid. Only by looking
at the developer effort (the rate of improvement) can we draw any conclusions about the effectiveness of
system design.</p>
<h3 id='footnotes'>Footnotes</h3><ul><li><p>* We, and not Kaashoek himself, call it Kaashoek’s Law, because it was inspired by his talk at CMU during the
ASPLOS 2011 PC meeting.</p>
</li><li><p>&dagger; Similarly, this statement was inpired by a private communication with Greg Ganger.</p>
</li></ul><h3 id='references'>References</h3><ol><a id='ref_1'></a><li><p>S. Boyd-Wickizer, A. Clements, Y. Mao, A. Pesterev, M. F. Kaashoek, R. Morris, and N. Zeldovich. An analysis of linux scalability to many cores. In <em>Proceedings of the 9th USENIX
Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation</em> (OSDI ’10), Vancouver, Canada, October 2010.</p>
</li><a id='ref_2'></a><li><p>Freebsd smpng project. http://freebsd.org/smp.</p>
</li><a id='ref_3'></a><li><p>NICTA. L4 performance. http://ertos.nicta.com.au/research/l4/performance.pml.</p>
</li><a id='ref_4'></a><li><p>P. Druschel, V. Pai, and W. Zwaenepoel. Extensible kernels are leading os research astray.
In <em>Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems</em> (HotOS-VI), pages 38–,
Washington, DC, USA, 1997. IEEE Computer Society.</p>
</li></ol>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/kaashoeks-law</guid></item><item><title>The Freedom to Compute (Repost from FidoNews)</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/fidonet-the-freedom-to-compute</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>This is a <a  href='http://www.wps.com/J/FidoNet/FidoNews/1986/FIDO311.NWS' title=''>reposting</a>
of an editorial written in FidoNews published on March
17th, 1986 by Mike Guffey. FidoNews is the newsletter of the FidoNet distributed network which
was a network of dialup BBSes that could share information. It was the first wide network that
allowed the public to communicate globally for free.</em></strong></p>

<p><strong><em>As this was written in the mid 80s, there is a strong anti-soviet/communism
and pro-american viewpoint. At the time, FidoNet was young and mostly had an
American audience. FidoNet has been recently used in areas where internet
censorship is prevalent. Interestingly, one
<a  href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5XFmXp0-KHA' title=''>such use</a>
is within former-soviet
states along the border of Russia who actively resist Russian control.</em></strong></p>

<p><strong><em>The Freedom to Compute: The human right to use a computational model to derive
any result.</em></strong></p>

<hr>

<p>Professor <a  href='http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/graham.html' title=''>Loren  Graham</a>
of  M.I.T.  recently  wrote  an  article
entitled  <em>&quot;The  Kremlin and the Computer&quot;</em>.  He depicted life with
state controlled computing.  His observation that  George  Orwell
had  it  all backwards in <em>&quot;1984&quot;</em> is shrewd.  He noted that Orwell
thought technology would allow &quot;Big Brother&quot; to maintain control.
Who would have guessed the Soviet Union would turn the tables and
retain control  by  the  suppression  of  technology,  especially
computer technology?</p>

<p>If   America&#39;s   government  relied  on  keeping  the  population
uninformed to retain power and control, things would be different
today.  What if your government didn&#39;t permit computer access  to
large amounts of accurate data,  didn&#39;t permit free communication
between computer users?  What if your government would not  allow
widespread   use   of  personal  computers  for  fear  of  losing
&quot;control&quot;?  How long could your government hope to genuinely keep
pace in the information age?</p>

<p>These were questions Graham explored in his article.  He  painted
a  grim  picture of what might be called &quot;retrograde technology&quot;.
He points out some democratic traditions indicating an edge  over
communist [and third world] nations:</p>
<ul><li><p>A  tradition  of  successful technology developed under private
ownership and control.</p>
</li><li><p>Close relationships between creators,  buyers  and  sellers  of
technology</p>
</li><li><p>A  tradition  of free access to and creation of massive amounts
of reliable information about most topics.</p>
</li><li><p>Excellent communications facilities  necessary  for  access  to
diverse and far-flung data bases.</p>
</li><li><p>A tradition of entrepreneurial and innovative freedom .</p>
</li></ul>
<p>Graham   goes  on  to  say,</p>

<blockquote>
<p>So  far  the  pattern  [of  Soviet
authorities] seems  to  be  to  require  that  all  computers  be
institutionally  housed  and controlled.  But what [they] may not
have realized is that they will pay a stiff price...  by severely
limiting  the rapidity of the growth of the computer culture,  by
hampering the spread of computer  literacy  among  young  people,
...by  watching the West become a true &#39;information society&#39; they
will be doomed to follow...&quot;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Graham also calls the  Soviet  Union
&quot;the  most  secretive  industrialized power in the world&quot;.  These
observations are based on  a  recent  visit  to  Moscow  and  his
background in the history of science.</p>

<p>There  is  no  known &quot;hacker-culture&quot; in the Soviet Union and its
youth is missing out on the experiences available to millions  of
American  schoolkids,  hobbyists  and  average  business computer
users.  Nor does the Soviet Union&#39;s educational system  emphasize
hands-on  experience  with high-technology hardware.  Even typing
is not widely taught.</p>

<p>Graham&#39;s article raises the question about how  long  the  Soviet
Union can retain a genuinely international status with a decaying
economy  that  can  neither heal itself with accurate information
nor give its children a legacy of competition in an  increasingly
computer-aided  world.  Surely a disturbing question for an aging
leadership.</p>

<p>So what about your most taken-for-granted freedom?  How important
is it to you?  What are you planning to do to protect it?  Unlike
the gun control or right-to-life issues,  the freedoms you  enjoy
in accessing as much (or as little) information as you desire are
seldom  regarded  as  burning  issues.  Are you to allowing it to
slip away as the communications giants gradually make  the  price
of information prohibitive?</p>

<p>In  earlier  times,  free  enterprise  aviation developed rapidly
because suffocating regulation had not yet  arrived  and  no  one
thought  to make air corridors into tollways.  Later,  after long
years of gradually instituted legislation,  many industry  giants
couldn&#39;t  survive  their  emancipation.  Today  our  situation is
reversed.  We have started out on overcrowded highways controlled
by one giant.  Let us hope the giant remains benevolent.  Let  us
hope  the  giant  doesn&#39;t team up with the federal bureaucracy to
act on our behalf without our consent.</p>

<p>Just where does one suggest a constitutional amendment?</p>

<hr>

<p><strong><em>This article illustrates the notion that controlling computation
may be a means of controlling information. I find it intriguing
that this thought existed as early as 1986. This predates the
<a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_fraud_and_abuse_act' title=''>Computer Fraud and Abuse Act</a>
which is overused against those attempting to spread information, and predates the attack on public
cryptography with the <a  href='http://www.usnews.com/usnews/news/articles/950403/archive_010975.htm' title=''>Arms Export Control Act</a>.
It came before the public internet and the cloud infrastructure that has both opened
the door to greater public usage of infrastructure, yet also promoted heavily
privatized control over user content. Have we improved? Do these modern incidents
and even designs of software and networks reinforce a lack of freedom
to compute?</em></strong></p>

<p><strong><em>Is the freedom to compute, for instance the ability to use our devices
to generate and access any information, something we need to more aggressively
fight for?</em></strong></p>

<hr>

<p>If you&#39;d like more information about FidoNet, there is an entire episode
dedicated to the network you can <a  href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QlXNXdf6Xh0' title=''>watch</a>
from the great Jason Scott documentary, <a  href='http://www.bbsdocumentary.com/' title=''>BBS Documentary</a>.
DVDs of the creative commons content are available on the website for the documentary.
Very much a recommended watch (this episode and the HPAC episode especially.)</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/fidonet-the-freedom-to-compute</guid></item><item><title>A Language for Interfaces</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/a-language-for-interfaces</link><description><![CDATA[<p>In my <a  href='/posts/djehuty-technical' title=''>technical description</a>, I described the motivation for a new infrastructure for software to stress a decentralized code ecosystem. From there I discuss the <a  href='/posts/infrastructure' title=''>finer details of such an infrastructure</a>. I recommend reading these before you read this article. The gist is that we want to describe behaviors distinctly from the choices made within implementations. Think C&#39;s header files versus the corresponding source files, but with far more purpose.</p>
<h2 id='what_we_need'>What we need</h2>
<p>As discussed in a <a  href='/posts/infrastructure' title=''>prior post</a>, we require the ability to describe a set of facets of a behavior:</p>
<ul><li>We must have a language that describes behavior void of policy
</li><li>Implementations of behavior must be flexible
</li><li>Behaviors are an interface and a specification
</li></ul>
<p>This implies we require a language that defines as few rules as possible, while giving you the power to define rules as you need to in order to describe behavior. Explicit rules, no implicit ones. C is an example of a language that attempts this, but it is not sufficient, as I will describe later.</p>

<p>Also, with the second point, the language we need is one where implementations are not tied to the interface description. Think of a C header file where the source file that implements it is not C. This is possible with languages that can export C functions, and I do not consider some shims/bridges to totally violate this idea. The languages that fall out will be languages which do not work well with others. The language will be, with this in mind, a systems oriented language (honing in on C, C++, D, Rust, Go)</p>

<p>Closing on the third point, being able to describe an interface and also test it without respect of the implementation is not something that is necessarily language specific. It need not limit our choice of language. However, it does encourage our interfaces to have very well-defined inputs and outputs. This includes describing whether or not inputs can change, whether they are passed by reference, or whether the inputs given are defined as never-changing (immutable). This also applies to state described in data types described outside of and shared by implementations.</p>

<p>Given this, we will add more refined rules for what we need from an interface language:</p>
<ul><li>Systems focus
</li><li>Lack of a defined memory model
</li><li>Typing is static, nominal, preferably subtyped
</li></ul>
<p>We care surprisingly little about, due to relegation to implementations, the following:</p>
<ul><li>Object orientedness, polymorphism, inheritance
</li><li>Concurrency, Thread models
</li><li>Garbage collection
</li></ul>
<p>That is, implementations may require a garbage collector, pull memory from a different memory pool, use different pieces of hardware, make use of a virtual machine, etc. This has nothing to do with the relationship between input and output. If an implementation of a parser interface is written in Rust, however, the memory model enforced by Rust may conflict with other implementations, the goal for this entire project is that another implementation can be found to route around the language choice.</p>

<p>In essence, language choices can not interfere with individuals finding and making use of software. This is why we strive for the lowest common denominator in our interface language.</p>
<h2 id='the_interface_language'>The Interface Language</h2>
<p>The language that I feel fits these constraints is a subset of Rust. What we will do is take Rust and remove its concurrency model, thus it&#39;s process model, and then we remove some of the strictness and garbage collected nature of its memory model. This requires negating some of the strengths of its concurrency safety, but that can be added back in by using Rust as the implementation language. It also removes the utility of Rust&#39;s managed boxes, since we do not imply a garbage collector (again the implementor&#39;s choice.)</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/a-language-for-interfaces/rust.png' title='' alt='The Rust programming language, developed by Mozilla Research, is an ideal platform for an interface language' /><br /><div class='caption'>The Rust programming language, developed by Mozilla Research, is an ideal platform for an interface language</div></div><p></p>

<p>Essentially, although we don&#39;t need a full language, the resulting language would be a C replacement on its own. It is interesting that we continue to replace C++ or some higher-level languages over C, which has not seen as much progress. It would stress the following:</p>
<ul><li>The type safety of Rust (to counter the lack of proper type checking in C)
</li><li>Macros instead of a preprocessor
</li><li>No null type with subtypes being used for errors
</li><li>Memory model is relegated to libraries
</li><li>Mutability adjectives for inputs and outputs and fields of structs/datatypes
</li></ul>
<p>We do not need the full C-replacement language for simply defining interfaces. Initially, we only need the ability to describe and thus a simple lexer/parser. But the full thing would be nice to have as a consequence! I encourage anybody with the desire to do this.</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/a-language-for-interfaces</guid></item><item><title>Learning Mistakes from Doom Masters</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/learning-mistakes-from-doom-masters</link><description><![CDATA[<p>So, right now, and every year, the Speedrun Demos Archive (<a  href='http://speeddemosarchive.com' title=''>speeddemosarchive.com</a>) runs a marathon (I&#39;m not directly involved) where they play video games and exploit glitches 24 hours a day for 7 days. They are promoting a great charity called the <a  href='http://preventcancer.org' title=''>Prevent Cancer Foundation</a> which hopes to aid in the research effort for better detection of cancer in hopes of eradicating it forever.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/learning-mistakes-from-doom-masters/prevent-cancer.png' title='' alt='!Prevent Cancer logo' /></div><p></p>

<p>As a hobby speedrunner, programmer and hater of cancer, in my own way to promote their event, I am inspired to talk about how these two concepts (our code and our mistakes) can be used to create art.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s be very clear: we all make mistakes. We cannot learn unless we fail, otherwise there is never an incentive to improve. We may look up to many who have more experience than us, but we should never emphasize their achievements over our own. In the end, what we are capable of is never defined by what others can do. Nor are the mistakes we make indicative of our failure or depict our work as flawed.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/learning-mistakes-from-doom-masters/doom.gif' title='' alt='Doom, released in 1993, is now open source-- and riddled with interesting programming mistakes.' /><br /><div class='caption'>Doom, released in 1993, is now open source-- and riddled with interesting programming mistakes.</div></div><p></p>

<p>As proof of this point, we will look at bugs humbly illustrated by <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_D._Carmack' title=''>John Carmack</a>, a programmer chiefly responsible for the video game <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(video_game)' title=''>Doom</a>. Carmack is very well known for his programming prowess. However, just like the rest of us, he is actually human and makes the very simplest of mistakes.</p>

<p>To show the art of the bug exploit, we will look at <strong>speedrunning</strong>. <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speedrun' title=''>Speedrunning</a> is a concept where a player attempts to complete a video game challenge as quickly as possible. Speedrunners are typically allowed to break the game in any way. They see code as the rules of the game, and anything the code allows is proper. In Doom, these expert players take advantage of several very basic and simple mistakes in the Doom code.</p>
<h2 id='speedrun_strategies'>Speedrun Strategies</h2>
<p>For speedrunning, you are obviously looking for any strategy that allows you to move just a bit faster. There are strategies for speedrunning particular levels of Doom, however there are several general techniques, which prove to be invaluable across the entire game. For Doom, it just so happens that we have the speedrunner&#39;s dream: a simple glitch in the movement code allows us to move faster than intended.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/learning-mistakes-from-doom-masters/doom-e1m4-gap.png' title='' alt='This gap contains the end of the level and normally requires a switch past this yellow door, which in turn requires a blue key. Crossing this gap is possible with a bug that allows you to move more quickly, skipping all keys, and finishing the level in a record 12 seconds.' /><br /><div class='caption'>This gap contains the end of the level and normally requires a switch past this yellow door, which in turn requires a blue key. Crossing this gap is possible with a bug that allows you to move more quickly, skipping all keys, and finishing the level in a record 12 seconds.</div></div><p></p>

<p>This has broad implications. Moving faster means jumping higher and farther (In Doom&#39;s case, you cannot jump, but you can cross wider gaps!) Some levels intend you to go out of your way to find a switch to raise a bridge, for instance. With a trick that lets you move faster, you might be able to cross the gap without the platform, which means skipping much of the level.</p>

<p>Here are the two movement tricks we will look at:</p>
<ul><li>(Strafe 40) Moving forward while also strafing in either direction will allow you to move 28% faster.
</li><li>(Strafe 50) Moving forward while also strafing in either direction while also toggling a feature that interprets turning as strafing allows you to move 41% faster.
</li></ul>
<p>Check out how this speedrunner runs:</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><div class='youtube'><div class='youtube_fixture'><img src='/images/youtube_placeholder.png' /><iframe class='youtube_frame' src='http://www.youtube.com/embed/M6PK9bd_uUs'></iframe></div></div><br /><div class='caption'>Rarely will this runner ever travel in the direction the player is facing.</div></div><p></p>
<h2 id='looking_at_the_code'>Looking at the code</h2>
<p>Let&#39;s now investigate why these particular bugs happen. Doom is written in [C](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C<em>(programming</em>language)), which is a very low-level programming language, meaning it is designed for speed and not particularly for programmer comfort. This was a very common language to write games in at the time since the language allowed you to write very optimized code so one could push the limits of the technology.</p>

<p>In the <a  href='https://github.com/osgcc/doom' title=''>Doom source</a>, there are several functions that deal with moving the player. The gist of them is that each frame before it draws the screen, it will decide how to move the player. It looks at which keys are pressed, and if, for instance, the walk forward key is down, it will update the player&#39;s position to move them forward. It may then look at collisions and react to running into monster projectiles, but let&#39;s just focus on the movement part.</p>
<h3 id='strafe_40'>Strafe 40</h3>
<p>Let&#39;s start with the first bug: the strafe 40, which is triggered simply by moving forward and strafing at the same time. So, we will investigate the <a  href='https://github.com/osgcc/DOOM/blob/master/linuxdoom-1.10/p_user.c#L148-171' title=''>code</a> that moves the player:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>void P_MovePlayer (player_t* player) {
  ticcmd_t* cmd;
  cmd = &amp;player-&gt;cmd;

  // Turn the player
  player-&gt;mo-&gt;angle += (cmd-&gt;angleturn&lt;&lt;16);

  // Do not let the player control movement
  // if not onground.
  onground = (player-&gt;mo-&gt;z &lt;= player-&gt;mo-&gt;floorz);

  // Move the player forward, if allowed
  if (cmd-&gt;forwardmove &amp;&amp; onground)
    P_Thrust (player, player-&gt;mo-&gt;angle, cmd-&gt;forwardmove*2048);

  // Move the player sideways, if allowed
  if (cmd-&gt;sidemove &amp;&amp; onground)
    P_Thrust (player, player-&gt;mo-&gt;angle-ANG90, cmd-&gt;sidemove*2048);
} 
</code></pre>
<p>In this function, the <code>cmd</code> element holds the distances to move per frame. <code>cmd&#8209;&gt;forwardmove</code> and <code>cmd&#8209;&gt;sidemove</code> contain the distances to travel either ahead of the player or to the side of the player respectively. It will set a <code>onground</code> value to true if the player&#39;s z position (how high off the ground) matches that of the floor the player is currently over. Therefore, it only wants to move if the player is in contact with the ground.</p>

<p>Given that the player is on the ground, the code checks to see if the player is due to move forward (<code>cmd&#8209;&gt;forwardmove</code> will be non-zero) and then calls another piece of code that simply repositions the player to reflect that movement. It does the same thing for a strafe.</p>

<p>From here, we can see the mistake. We can move forward or strafe independently, and it would work as expected. However, if we move forward <strong>and</strong> strafe, the player will thrust forward, and then afterward, thrust sideways. However, these two movements are done at the same time from the perspective of the game and player because both are done before the screen is drawn and enemies react. Therefore, the actual speed is given by the sum of the vectors; that is, the length of the hypotenuse in the following simple diagram:</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/learning-mistakes-from-doom-masters/doom-strafe40.svg' title='' alt='Strafe 40: By strafing and moving forward independently, we actually move to the far corner, which covers the distance of the hypotenuse during the same amount of time, thus going faster.' /><br /><div class='caption'><strong>Strafe 40</strong>: By strafing and moving forward independently, we actually move to the far corner, which covers the distance of the hypotenuse during the same amount of time, thus going faster.</div></div><p></p>
<h3 id='fixing_strafe_40'>Fixing strafe 40</h3>
<p>There are of course many ways to repair this bug and handle movement more correctly. One way is to, instead of positioning the player twice, determine the angle of the movement, and always use the same distance. That is, instead of moving in the player&#39;s direction and then moving again in another direction for the strafe, simply calculate the movement angle (around 50 degrees for walking and strafing), and <code>P_Thrust</code> only once in that direction.</p>

<p>Notice that the code does not account for which direction you are strafing. This is because of a naive optimization: the distance (in the code this is the <code>cmd&#8209;&gt;forwardmove * 2048</code>) you give to <code>P_Thrust</code> can be negative to move in the opposite direction. For the fix, you will have to account for the direction you are strafing to get the correct angle, but now you always give a positive distance.</p>
<h3 id='strafe_50'>Strafe 50</h3>
<p>To understand how to exploit the next vulnerability, we have to look at how it decides <code>cmd&#8209;&gt;forwardmove</code> and <code>cmd&#8209;&gt;sidemove</code>. These values determine how many units the player will travel per frame in those directions. The flaw is that you can artificially affect these values by having the game accidentally count two different keys as movement during a single frame.</p>

<p>Basically, you tell it to move you to the right... twice, and it diligently listens to you. For this, let&#39;s look at the <a  href='https://github.com/osgcc/DOOM/blob/master/linuxdoom-1.10/g_game.c#L237-437' title=''>input handling code</a>:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>void G_BuildTiccmd (ticcmd_t* cmd) {
  boolean strafe;
  int speed;
  int forward;
  int side;

  // We are strafing if a strafe key is pressed
  strafe = gamekeydown[key_strafe];

  // Is the run key pressed?
  speed  = gamekeydown[key_speed];

  // The distances we are moving are initially zero
  forward = side = 0;

  // Determine distances to move
  if (strafe) {
<div class='ref_line s1 c1'><div>    // If the strafe toggle is on, interpret moving left and right
    //   as strafing left and right.
    if (gamekeydown[key_right]) // Strafe right&lt;/span&gt;
      side += sidemove[speed];
    if (gamekeydown[key_left])  // Strafe left
      side -= sidemove[speed];
</div></div>  }
  else {
    if (gamekeydown[key_right]) // Move right
      cmd-&gt;angleturn -= angleturn[tspeed];
    if (gamekeydown[key_left])  // Move left
      cmd-&gt;angleturn += angleturn[tspeed];
  }

  if (gamekeydown[key_up])   // Move forward
    forward += forwardmove[speed];
  if (gamekeydown[key_down]) // Move backward
    forward -= forwardmove[speed];

<div class='ref_line s1 c2'><div>  // Strafe right
  if (gamekeydown[key_straferight])
    side += sidemove[speed];
</div></div>
  // Strafe left
  if (gamekeydown[key_strafeleft])
    side -= sidemove[speed];

<div class='ref_line s1 c3'><div>  // Cap speed
  if (side &gt; forwardmove[speed])
    side = forwardmove[speed];
  else if (side &lt; -forwardmove[speed])
    side = -forwardmove[speed]; 
</div></div>
  cmd-&gt;forwardmove += forward;
  cmd-&gt;sidemove += side;
} 
</code></pre>
<p>We can see the familiar <code>cmd&#8209;&gt;forwardmove</code> and <code>cmd&#8209;&gt;sidemove</code> at the bottom. Ah! So this is the code that determines those! So, how does it translate the key presses into meaningful values in the game?</p>

<p>Well, in Doom, we can strafe one of two ways:</p>
<ul><li>A key that toggles strafe so that left and right do not turn you, but rather make you move sideways.
</li><li>A dedicated strafe key for each direction, which works the same way as the A or D keys on most modern games.
</li></ul>
<p>Now, with that in mind, look at the code. In section <code>1</code>, we see that the game looks to see if that strafe toggle is held. Depending on that, it either stores the <code>cmd&#8209;&gt;angleturn</code> which tells the <code>P_MovePlayer</code> function above to turn the given degrees before drawing. Or it completely ignores the turning and instead strafes by adding a distance to move (affected by whether or not run is enabled) to the variable <code>side</code>, which is initially zero.</p>

<p>So, ok. We know that when we have the strafe toggle on, and we press the right arrow key, it will handle that as a strafe to the right and add some distance to the variable <code>side</code>. However, note section <code>2</code>, which happens independently of the strafe toggle. If you also press the strafe right key, this code will add more to the current value (<code>side += sidemove[speed]</code> is the same as writing <code>side = side + sidemove[speed]</code>). Well, that means if we press the dedicated strafe right key <strong>and</strong> we also press right while the strafe toggle is on, then we will effectively strafe twice!</p>

<p>Interestingly, the programmer was not very optimistic about the code and if you look at section <code>3</code>, you&#39;ll notice that the speed of side movement is capped to the maximum speed you can run forward. However, this caps the sideways strafe speed incorrectly to that of 50 units per second, which is still faster than the maximum strafing speed of 40! Since this does not interfere with the strafing bug we investigated earlier, we just found a way to make it more effective.</p>

<p>The diagram becomes:</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/learning-mistakes-from-doom-masters/doom-strafe50.svg' title='' alt='Strafe 50: By strafing using both the strafe key and using the strafe toggle, we trick the game into strafing more than once and go just a bit faster.' /><br /><div class='caption'><strong>Strafe 50</strong>: By strafing using both the strafe key and using the strafe toggle, we trick the game into strafing more than once and go just a bit faster.</div></div><p></p>
<h3 id='fixing_strafe_50'>Fixing strafe 50</h3>
<p>Even though this bug seems more severe and tricky, it&#39;s far easier to solve than strafe 40. All you need to do is put the code in section <code>2</code> into the else block after section <code>1</code> such that the normal strafe is only considered if strafe toggle is off.</p>

<p>Alternatively, to allow for strafe to be pressed by the dedicated strafe key even if strafe toggle is on, just fix the code in section <code>3</code>. Instead of capping it to the forward movement speed, use the strafe movement speed:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>// Cap speed
if (side &gt; sidemove[speed])
  side = sidemove[speed];
else if (side &lt; -sidemove[speed])
  side = -sidemove[speed]; 
</code></pre>
<p>This will ensure strafe 50 is no longer a problem. You will now not be able to do any better than the original strafe 40.</p>
<h2 id='your_turn'>Your turn</h2>
<p>You can try these tricks as well! <a  href='http://store.steampowered.com/app/2280' title=''>Grab a copy</a> of Doom and try running through the levels. Use the cheat code <code>idclev14</code> to go to the level the screen cap above illustrates. You can find a guide to other strategies <a  href='http://doomwiki.org/wiki/E1M4' title=''>here</a>.</p>

<p>On Thursday at around 8:45pm EST, the Speed Demos Archive charity will be live speed demoing the entire Doom game while giving further commentary on the techniques. Please, <a  href='http://marathon.speeddemosarchive.com/' title=''>go watch</a> (right now, in fact, for other games!) and consider donating to Prevent Cancer for prizes and general well-being. Here is a <a  href='http://marathon.speeddemosarchive.com/schedule' title=''>schedule</a>.</p>
<h2 id='making_mistakes'>Making mistakes</h2>
<p>As you can see, these mistakes were made by otherwise great programmers. These bugs are very simple, although a little hard to spot. All of us are capable of writing code and only considering one case at a time (does moving forward work? good. Does moving sideways work? Awesome,) and never considering somebody will mash all of the keys at once. We&#39;re all human.</p>

<p>We must understand one thing: It&#39;s not the end of the world. With every bug we make, we learn. In fact, sometimes our bugs make somebody&#39;s day! Speedrunning is an artform that proves that our code and our mistakes can be turned into a beautiful spectacle that we should never be ashamed of.</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/learning-mistakes-from-doom-masters</guid></item><item><title>Conferences Must Be Active to Promote Diversity</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/conference_diversity</link><description><![CDATA[<p>In the spring of 2012, the <a  href='http://britruby.com' title=''>BritRuby</a> conference presented their speaker lineup. They decide to invite 15 speakers and then
allot 5 more to select later based on submissions. However, their speaker lineup was later <a  href='https://twitter.com/joshsusser/status/269844125363339264' title=''>contested heavily on twitter</a> due to consisting of all white men. Due to this,
the organizers decided to <a  href='http://2013.britruby.com/' title=''>cancel</a> the conference altogether.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Nice speaker lineup for BritRuby. Except for the 100% white guys part.</p>

<div class="citation">&mdash; Josh Susser, organizer of Golden Gate RubyConf, <a href="https://twitter.com/joshsusser/status/269844125363339264">on twitter</a></div>
</blockquote>
<h2 id='the_conference_that_is_critical_of_voice'>The conference that is critical of voice</h2>
<p>It is a very dangerous proposition to suggest that the conversations on Twitter that indeed led to the demise of the conference
should have been suppressed. To say such a thing, and it has <a  href='https://gist.github.com/4106776' title=''>been said</a>, would be tantamount to suggesting that the value of
holding the conference surpasses the value of an expression of equal rights. It would be as though the conference as it stood would be better
than the ideal function of such a venue to provide a fair and equal platform for being heard. Certainly a venue of communication that
fails to provide equal voice is devalued over that voice?</p>

<p>Let&#39;s look at the math. The likelihood that a selection process that is blind to gender would select certain combinations of men and women
is a simple Bernoulli distribution. I&#39;m going to assume a gender binary for simplicity and discuss the notion of not selecting women. They
are the largest unrepresented group and among underrepresented groups, they enjoy the most privilege. Therefore, anything dismissing women must also be dismissing minority
groups.</p>

<p><a  href='http://cra.org/uploads/documents/resources/taulbee/CRA_Taulbee_2011-2012_Results.pdf' title=''>Taubee studies</a> show that women earn 20% of the degrees in computer science. That being my best statistic, I will assume
that 20% of women are involved in the tech field in some way. That implies the expected number of women speakers would be 3, not 0, although to match the true population we
would ideally shoot for a 1:1 ratio in all regards (degree awardees, conference speaking, etc) and look for about 7 to 8. With that in mind, the probabilities given a field of 15 speakers are as follows:</p>
<h3 id='probabilities_of_outcomes_given_random_selection_'>Probabilities of outcomes given random selection:</h3><pre><code class='lang-'>15 men and  0 women =  3.5%  &lt;-- Observed
14 men and  1 women = 13.1%
13 men and  2 women = 23.0%
12 men and  3 women = 25.0%  &lt;-- Expected (Against number of CS degree awardees)
11 men and  4 women = 18.7%
10 men and  5 women = 10.3%
9  men and  6 women =  4.2%
8  men and  7 women =  1.3%  &lt;-- Ideal (Against world population)
7  men and  8 women = ~0.3%
6  men and  9 women = ~0.0%
</code></pre><h3 id='probability_of_having___'>Probability of having...</h3><pre><code class='lang-'>=0  women:  3.5%  &lt;-- Observed
&gt;0  women: 96.5%
&gt;1  women: 83.4%
&gt;2  women: 60.4%  &lt;-- Expected (Against number of CS degree awardees)
&gt;3  women: 35.4%  &lt;-- It is more likely to have more than the expected number
&gt;4  women: 16.7%      than to have exactly no women represented.
&gt;5  women:  6.4%
&gt;6  women:  2.2%  &lt;-- Ideal (Against world population)
&gt;7  women:  0.9%
&gt;8  women: ~0.0%
=0  men:   ~0.0%
</code></pre>
<p>The probability of such an arrangement, by blind review, suggests one of two things: either women are extremely unqualified to be
leaders in this area / have no such interest by virtue of genetics due to the fact that their proposals were deemed less interesting or vital
compared to men. Or <strong>there is no such correlation and women are intellectually equal to men and the system of organization that prevails in this culture
has oppressed their ability to be visible</strong>. The former claim is preposterous given our scientific knowledge that gender differences are
not biological, especially in terms of intelligence, problem solving, and interest. They are indeed constructed from a series of social
factors, such as the well-studied stereotype threat. Therefore, it is far more likely that the social factors that obscure women from
being represented include the subconscious bias against them represented here by the conference speaker lineup.</p>

<p>The solution is to actively promote such diversity and be proud of supporting it. But affirmative action is bad, they say. It hurts the meritocracy, they say.
To suggest that a (specifically. as in, the adjective was actually actively <a  href='https://gist.github.com/4106776' title=''>used in opposition</a>.) token minority would not be acceptable is to suggest that
no such qualified speaker is available. &quot;How dare we push an African speaker just because of their skin color! They couldn&#39;t possibility have anything of value to
say! A woman? No, she failed to pass our rigorous test. There is no way her input could ever be valid!&quot; Yes, it is a ridiculous thing to say. I agree. But this
is a valid interpretation of that argument. It suggests a speaker of quality that happens to be a woman or within a minority group does not exist.</p>

<p>We must acknowledge that
this is not only false, but a rather dismissive idea that serves only to diminish the voice of an already relatively invisible
section of our community. We should be taking the effort to help those in this situation to be heard. Look for quality, and you shall find it,
  and you can promote it with, yes, special focused effort. This conference did not do this, has a statistically significant disparity, and
was called out upon it rightfully. <strong>If you as a conference are inviting speakers and actively looking for quality yet not actively promoting diversity, then you are not trying hard enough.</strong> Even if you criticize my numbers and suggest that, although 20% of the community are women, more percentage of men than women want to speak. That&#39;s
still a problem! A problem a conference must be willing to solve by actively promoting voice so that there are more potential voices
through the dispelling of stereotypes and better, more visible role models.</p>

<p>Considering the effect occurs on the most optimistic of cases (providing a voice for women) and this voice is being suppressed, it only follows that
other voices of minority communities that are far less represented are being oppressed considerably more. Since the number of active voices in the
CS community for those of African ethnicity are <a  href='http://www.math.buffalo.edu/mad/computer-science/cs-peeps.html' title=''>less than 1%</a>, the probability distribution shifts dramatically toward the choosing of just one individual
in a blind review (just by chance!) becoming nearly a miracle. Therefore, a blind review cannot capture a diversity of voice, and organizers must
be more active to promote a higher probability and thus opportunity to those voices that go unheard. Is it fair that your system of assessment is devised by
the least diverse group you can build? Communicate with others and consult with diverse community leaders to bring their knowledge to more people.
That should be what your conference is about: being heard.</p>
<h3 id='probability_proofs'>Probability Proofs</h3>
<p>I have developed a small program that produces the probability distribution of gender selection
for tech events in a <a  href='https://gist.github.com/4114968' title=''>gist found here</a>. Included with this is
a simulation experiment that shows just how unlikely the situation that resulted in this conference
really is. This simulation should affirm the mathematics as well.</p>
<h3 id='blind_review_correlation'>Blind Review Correlation</h3>
<p>Some have pointed out that comparing the handpicking scenario of BritRuby does not compare to the blind evaluation presented here. However, it does indeed compare. If your handpicking process is blind to gender (assuming that intellectual capacities are also gender-neutral) then your process will yield the same gender distribution as a blind review. The point is that their process did not do so, and now we can draw valid conclusions about the bias that exists. We can now say, &quot;their selection process is biased against women.&#39; Furthermore, we can draw some hypotheses that the representation of minorities is also not being considered. This is damning. We must also conclude that bringing awareness to this issue was correct as long as we suggest that bias should not occur in speaker selection at conferences.</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/conference_diversity</guid></item><item><title>Curriculum Vitae</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/cv</link><description><![CDATA[<p>My name is Dave Wilkinson, better known as <strong><em>wilkie</em></strong>. I develop large scale distributed systems and am looking for a position that will allow me to use that specialization to make better the open web. I have a strong desire to develop technology that can be accessed by anybody and push progress of a public commons without constraint. I specialize in the research and development of low-level distributed systems that reduce barriers of entry and push more control, authority, and rights to those that use the system. My overall goal is to provide a system that guarantees the freedom to compute.</p>
<h2 id='education'>Education</h2><ul><li><strong>College</strong>: University of Pittsburgh, 2005-2009
</li><li><strong>Degree</strong>: Bachelors with Honors, Computer Science
</li><li><strong>Post-Bachelors</strong>: Graduate study in CS, University of Pittsburgh, 2009-2012
</li></ul><h2 id='speaking'>Speaking</h2><ul><li><p><strong><em>Operating System Fundamentalism</em></strong> - <em>SOSP 2011</em> - Stressed new concerns and models for modern OS/kernel architectures to an audience of established systems researchers at a top systems conference. <a  href='http://sigops.org/sosp/sosp11/posters/summaries/sosp11-final39.pdf' title=''>Paper</a>. <a  href='http://sigops.org/sosp/sosp11/posters/posters/sosp11-display-poster39.pdf' title=''>Poster</a>.</p>
</li><li><p><strong><em>XOmB+Djehuty: Platform for Code Remix</em></strong> - <em>CSA 2013</em> - Discussed an operating system architecture that promotes better diversity and involvement of non-systems people in its creation and maintenance and how to promote better code reuse. Afterward, my co-speaker and I were invited to help plan and review proposals for the panel for next year. <a  href='https://speakerdeck.com/wilkie/xomb-plus-djehuty-a-remix-os-for-computation-liberation' title=''>Slides</a>.</p>
</li><li><p><strong><em>Social Computation and the Freedom to Compute</em></strong> - <em>PGHTechFest 2013</em> - A political view of the open source culture and how it actively discourages participation from the commons and is driven from a centralized, authoritarian development model and new models of systems that would solve these problems. <a  href='https://speakerdeck.com/wilkie/social-computation-the-freedom-to-compute' title=''>Slides</a>.</p>
</li></ul><h2 id='writing'>Writing</h2><ul><li><p><strong><em>XOmB: an Exokernel for Modern 64-bit Multicore Hardware</em></strong> - WSO - VII Workshop de Sistemas Operacionais - Belo Horizonte, Brasil - July, 2010. Describes the system architecture, technical merit, and novelty of a new kernel built without the legacy of prior abstractions. <a  href='http://www.inf.pucminas.br/sbc2010/anais/pdf/wso/st02_02.pdf' title=''>Full paper</a>.</p>
</li><li><p><strong><em>Balancing Performance, Accuracy, and Precision for Secure Cloud Transactions</em></strong> - IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems - August, 2013. Proposes new database consistency algorithms for emerging distributed data solutions to account for finer-grained privacy control within an eventually consistent environment. <a  href='/images/cv/TPDS_revision.pdf' title=''>Full paper</a>.</p>
</li><li><p><strong><em>Studying Speedrunners</em></strong> - Game Developer Magazine - March, 2013. A look at the bugs in the popular game DOOM that have been discovered over the years by enthusiast players. I examine the released source code to explain why certain tricks work and discuss why having bugs in your games can be part of its appeal, not a drawback or mistake. <a  href='http://gamedeveloper.texterity.com/gamedeveloper/201303?pg=57#article_id=262899' title=''>Full article</a>.</p>
</li></ul><h2 id='teaching'>Teaching</h2><ul><li><p><strong><em>Introduction to Java</em></strong> - Instructor, University of Pittsburgh - 2010-2011 - Taught for 3 consecutive semesters with an above-average student-evaluated teaching rating. Instructs beginner level Java programming for non-computer-science majors. Had full control over curriculum and planning devising homework assignments and exams. My curriculum experimented with interweaving computer art and culture into the discussion. One of my more celebrated/hated classes involved a group discussion of ethics involving free information and hacktivism, types of activities that programming skill may unlock.</p>
</li><li><p><strong><em>Introduction to Systems</em></strong> - Lab Instructor, University of Pittsburgh - 2011-2012 - Taught for 2 semesters. Taught C to computer science minors/majors with an emphasis on systems and low-level programming. Included labs on Makefiles, filesystem programming, and adding system calls to Linux.</p>
</li><li><p><strong><em>Open Source Game Coding Competition</em></strong> - Event organizer - 2009-present - Yearly competition that attracts around 30 participants per year devoted to beginners to motivate them to form teams with experienced programmers to pair and build video games to be released open source to help jumpstart similar beginners outside of the competition. I won the competition in its 2nd year and have ran the competition since then for the last 4 years. My responsibilities are to fund the event through sponsorship, advertise, organize judging, and make sure everybody is having fun. <a  href='http://osgcc.github.io' title=''>Website</a>. <a  href='https://github.com/osgcc' title=''>Competition Code</a>.</p>
</li></ul><h2 id='work_experience'>Work Experience</h2><ul><li><p><strong><em>Software Engineer</em></strong> - Vocollect - Summer of 2008 - Worked on their flagship product, a hand-held, voice-activated, programmable device typically used for warehouse workers or carriers for hands-free inventory. Embedded C/C++. Rewrote very low-level, core pieces of code to optimize and reduce initialization time by around 60 percent, a significant feat.</p>
</li><li><p><strong><em>Freelance Work</em></strong> - Summer of 2009 - Implemented a contract work within the period of two weeks to develop an iPhone application generator for the syndication of RSS/Atom feeds of audio/video podcasts into a custom styled app used to play the various episodes.</p>
</li><li><p><strong><em>Student Researcher</em></strong> - University of Pittsburgh - 2009-2012 - Researched operating system designs and distributed systems with an emphasis on building new systems.</p>
</li><li><p><strong><em>Teaching Fellow</em></strong> - University of Pittsburgh - 2010-2012 - Responsible for curriculum in introductory programming courses. See <a  href='#teaching' title=''>Teaching</a> section.</p>
</li></ul><h2 id='software'>Software</h2><h3 id='rstat_us__ruby_rails__javascript_coffeescript____web_application'>rstat.us (ruby/rails, javascript/coffeescript) - Web Application</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Source:</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh/rstat.us' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p></p><div class='image right border'><img src='/images/cv/rstatus.png' title='' alt='!rstatus screenshot' /></div><p></p>

<p>A free and open-source, federated microblogging platform I founded with a team of friends, resembling twitter and status.net, that emphasizes personal use and self-ownership of data. That is, this software is designed to be easily deployed on a hosting service or a personal server. The ownership and authority over the content is primarily in the hands of the individual, instead of a company that runs a centralized service such as twitter. It uses the <a  href='http://www.w3.org/community/ostatus/' title=''>ostatus</a> protocol to distribute content within a social graph to nodes and servers maintained by other people.</p>

<p>Considering it is a social system at heart that attempts to liberate data to individuals, rstat.us became very successful. The rate of adoption out-paced app.net with 6,000 unique users in our opening week. We have over 60 <a  href='https://rstat.us/about' title=''>contributors</a> from all across the world which further suggests its appeal and need in the global world. I am a core maintainer along with <a  href='http://carol-nichols.com/' title=''>Carol Nichols</a>, and help organize new feature efforts and review pull requests, although our development model allows for any past contributor to commit and merge at any time.</p>
<h3 id='lotus__ruby_sinatra__javascript____web_framework'>lotus (ruby/sinatra, javascript) - Web Framework</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Source:</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh/lotus' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p></p><div class='image right border'><img src='/images/cv/lotus.png' title='' alt='!lotus screenshot' /></div><p></p>

<p>Building off of the experience of building rstat.us, I started the Lotus project. While rstat.us was engineered to be a federated microblogging solution, it was not very conducive to building new types of federated, self-hosted websites. Therefore, I ripped out the backend of rstat.us and refined it. Lotus contains several sub-repositories that will allow you to build a federated website using simple building blocks.</p>

<p>This is very much an experiment in modular MVC. The <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh/lotus' title=''>lotus</a> base project contains the non-persistent models which define the data and relationships, useful for clients. The <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh/lotus-mongodb' title=''>lotus-mongodb</a> project adds persistence using mongodb, a useful key-value store for extensible data (where the schema is unknown.) The <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh/rack-lotus' title=''>rack-lotus</a> project contains the controllers and routes that drive the web API. To give you a base to start out from, the <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh/lotus-site' title=''>lotus-site</a> project gives a set of views and javascript already designed to produce a responsive website that can be easily extended. Furthermore, the <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh/lotus-i18n' title=''>lotus-i18n</a> project adds internationalization that will be shared among all federated sites.</p>

<p>With these base projects I have implemented a distributed, federated social framework for microblogging (tweets), blogging, and image sharing. It will be easy to add other types of sharable objects, and external systems hosted by others will gracefully support them even if they do not understand them. Any site that you produce with the framework will be easily deployable to enjoy a low barrier of entry for non-technical folks.</p>
<h3 id='xomb__d__assembly____systems_design_and_implementation'>xomb (D, assembly) - Systems Design and Implementation</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Source:</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/xomboverlord/xomb' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p></p><div class='image right border'><img src='/images/cv/xomb.png' title='' alt='!xomb screenshot' /></div><p></p>

<p>XOmB is a novel exokernel-inspired operating system project aimed at developing the most
flexible OS architecture possible as a means of building more efficient systems and building systems more efficiently.
Our immediate aim is to build a research and education platform, but by doing so we contend XOmB offers the
opportunity to develop more streamlined OS implementations for general purpose and server use. The flexibility we
aim to achieve should allow the same kernel to be deployed in many scenarios, adapting the userspace if needed.</p>

<p>The design of the XOmB kernel does not impose any unnecessary abstractions, and thus avoids hiding
state from the applications or incurring additional overheads (e.g. implementing a database on top of a filesystem
introduces numerous inefficiencies). Due to minimizing abstractions imposed by the OS, XOmB will be able to
provide a software base sufficient to build new interfaces without having to tear down or re-engineer the kernel.</p>

<p>We (myself and <a  href='http://wolfwood.github.io/2013/06/20/interface-fidelity.html' title=''>James Larkby-Lahet</a>) diverge significantly from prior efforts in our treatment of state with the XOmB exokernel. We relegate even
more kernel code to userspace libraries, which are untrusted and can be customized (completely modified or replaced)
on a per-application basis. We do so by extracting two key components of the exokernel: device drivers and system
state. These components are implemented in userspace where they are met with easy debugging and hardware enforced safety.</p>
<h3 id='gutenberg__ruby__javascript_jquery____content_generation'>gutenberg (ruby, javascript/jQuery) - Content Generation</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Source:</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/gutenberg' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p></p><div class='image right border'><img src='/images/cv/gutenberg.png' title='' alt='!gutenberg screenshot' /></div><p></p>

<p>I am very interested in hypermedia and exploring its use to transform traditional media into something more substantial in this information era. To that end, <em>gutenberg</em> is a project that turns a flavor of <a  href='http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/' title=''>markdown</a> into a website that is typeset using javascript code on the client side. The idea is that books can contain links to other books and other external information and to provide, eventually, a seamless experience in reading this information.</p>

<p>The project consists of ruby code that will render the markup into html, css, and images and package them with javascript. It is designed such that without javascript or using a screenreader (typically used by blind individuals), the book is still readable as a basic webpage. The book output can also be easily parsed by html parsers and generates a very minimal markup. The rest of the work to make the book into a dynamic frame with full typesetting is done completely in javascript. Styling can be provided by stylesheets and images provided by the library or easily extended by adding custom css and javascript.</p>

<p>An example of the project in action can be found <a  href='http://derailingfordummi.es' title=''>here</a> and compare this to the plain html without any javascript <a  href='http://derailingfordummi.es/?plain' title=''>here</a>.</p>
<h3 id='reuleaux_selectors__javascript____user_human_interfaces'>reuleaux-selectors (javascript) - User/Human Interfaces</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Source:</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/reuleaux-selectors' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p></p><div class='image right border'><img src='/images/cv/reuleaux-selectors.png' title='' alt='!gutenberg screenshot' /></div><p></p>

<p>As a queer individual, I&#39;m concerned with forms of available representation and allowances of diversity in the technological space. The role of personal gender identification is a part of human interfaces that has been untouched regardless of the fact that dropdown gender selection of simply male and female is unacceptable. Textfields, while better, allow for so much choice that people may pigeonhole themselves and would be otherwise incomparable.</p>

<p>Along with <a  href='http://rarlindseysmash.com' title=''>Lindsey Bieda</a>, we designed and <a  href='/posts/reuleaux-selectors' title=''>implemented</a> a new form of gender and sexuality selector that we feel is a stage of evolution that provides a familiar selector that is both comparable and highly representative of the queer identity. We see the primary use of such a selector for social networking sites as a means of representing oneself as one pleases, and also for dating services to offer better support for the preferences and identity of queer individuals.</p>

<p>Play around with the selectors <a  href='http://wilkie.github.io/reuleaux-selectors/' title=''>here</a>.</p>
<h3 id='apsis__c____assembly__glsl____general_purpose_game_engine'>apsis (C++, assembly, GLSL) - General-Purpose Game Engine</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Source:</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/apsis' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p></p><div class='image right border'><img src='/images/cv/apsis.png' title='' alt='!apsis screenshot' /></div><p></p>

<p>Going along with my <a  href='http://osgcc.github.io' title=''>open source game coding competition</a>, I am currently developing a free and open-source (early stages) game engine builder. To jumpstart games and creative expression, I have created a framework that gives you the building blocks for creating game engines.</p>

<p>Here is how it works: Create an Engine. Add a Map to draw tile-based maps. Add an Actor to represent the player. Attach an Up, Down, Left, Right modules to the player actor to give it a set of rules that let it respond to input and move in all four directions. Add a MapCollider rule so that you do not go through walls. You now have a basic <strong>top-down 2D scroller</strong> much like Zelda games. Remove the Up and Down rules on the player actor, and add Jump and Fall rules, and now you have a <strong>2D side-scroller</strong>.</p>

<p>By building games via a set of rules, you can be provided a set of predefined rules to quickly make traditional games, but also allow extensibility by defining new rules. This will be perfect in an educational environment where predefined rules can be used to get things rolling, but programming concepts can be introduced gradually to beginners when they want to do something fancy.</p>

<p>I hope to bind the logic and rule creation to a language that is better suited for beginners such as Lua or Ruby. That way, the game engine itself is written in OpenGL/C++ but the extensible components can be an easy to use scripting language.</p>
<h2 id='occasional_contribution'>Occasional Contribution</h2><ul><li><a  href='https://github.com/gittip/www.gittip.com/' title=''>gittip</a> - Python-based website for weekly tips to online creators.
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/sinatra/sinatra' title=''>sinatra</a> - Ruby rack-based web micro-framework.
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/shoes/shoes' title=''>shoes</a> - C library backend for the shoes ruby GUI framework.
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/hacketyhack/hacketyhack' title=''>hackety-hack</a> - Ruby educational tool to teach programming visually to beginners.
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/seangeo/ratom' title=''>ratom</a> - Ruby library for Atom feed generation.
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/ldc-developers/ldc' title=''>ldc</a> - D compiler frontend to LLVM.
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/intridea/redfinger' title=''>redfinger</a> - Ruby library for webfinger (distributed identity) polling.
</li></ul>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/cv</guid></item><item><title>Projects I am Involved With</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/projects</link><description><![CDATA[<h2 id='founded'>Founded</h2><h3 id='rstat_us'>rstat.us</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Language</em></strong> ruby
</li><li><strong><em>Status</em></strong> gamma
</li><li><strong><em>Source</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh/rstat.us' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p>A federated microblogging platform, resembling twitter and status.net, that emphasizes personal use and self-ownership of data. It uses the ostatus protocol.</p>
<h3 id='xomb'>xomb</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Language</em></strong> D
</li><li><strong><em>Status</em></strong> beta
</li><li><strong><em>Source</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/xomboverlord/xomb' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p>A exokernel-inspired kernel that uses modern hardware to provide a functional, general purpose, secure bare-metal systems layer.</p>
<h3 id='djehuty'>djehuty</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Language</em></strong> n/a
</li><li><strong><em>Status</em></strong> alpha
</li><li><strong><em>Source</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/djehuty/djehuty' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p>A public domain API infrastructure. This platform will emphasize many implementations, intelligent automated code selection, and encourages a build system that learns from the experience of machines it communicates with.</p>
<h3 id='ibis'>ibis</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Language</em></strong> n/a
</li><li><strong><em>Status</em></strong> alpha
</li><li><strong><em>Source</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/djehuty/ibis' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p>A set of initial, naive, implementations for djehuty platform.</p>
<h3 id='gruesome'>gruesome</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Language</em></strong> ruby
</li><li><strong><em>Status</em></strong> beta
</li><li><strong><em>Source</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/gruesome' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p>A public domain z-machine implementation capable of playing/displaying many interactive fictions, such as the original Zork.</p>
<h3 id='propeller'>propeller</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Language</em></strong> ruby
</li><li><strong><em>Status</em></strong> alpha
</li><li><strong><em>Source</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/propeller' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p>A system for managing addons and user defined configurations for projects, emphasizing ruby projects currently.</p>
<h3 id='ostatus_gem'>ostatus gem</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Language</em></strong> ruby
</li><li><strong><em>Status</em></strong> beta
</li><li><strong><em>Source</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh/ostatus' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p>A gem that helps ruby applications make use of the ostatus protocol.</p>
<h3 id='papyri'>papyri</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Language</em></strong> ruby
</li><li><strong><em>Status</em></strong> gamma
</li><li><strong><em>Source</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/djehuty/papyri' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p>A program that takes a uniform yaml description of an API and generates consistent html-based documentation.</p>
<h3 id='socrates'>socrates</h3><ul><li><strong><em>Language</em></strong> ruby
</li><li><strong><em>Status</em></strong> gamma
</li><li><strong><em>Source</em></strong> <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie/socrates' title=''>github</a>
</li></ul>
<p>A static-site-generator for generating course webpages. It allows for timed releases of resources, assignments, and solutions. It supports media formats for resources and generates an intuitive, but highly customizable, interface to access them.</p>
<h2 id='occasional_contribution'>Occasional Contribution</h2><ul><li><a  href='https://github.com/shoes/shoes' title=''>shoes</a>
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/hacketyhack/hacketyhack' title=''>hackety-hack</a>
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/seangeo/ratom' title=''>ratom</a>
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/ldc-developers/ldc' title=''>ldc</a>
</li><li><a  href='https://github.com/intridea/redfinger' title=''>redfinger</a>
</li></ul>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/projects</guid></item><item><title>The Djehuty Project - For The Technical Lot</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/djehuty-technical</link><description><![CDATA[<p><a  href='/posts/who-am-i' title=''>I</a> have a dream that we can solve the current crisis that is software. To do this, and this might seem ambitious but bear with me, we must burn every piece of structure we have to the ground. We must replace the structure around our software with a new infrastructure that gives us more sustainability and versatility. In the process we gain various technological and socialogical advantages.</p>
<h2 id='what_we_have_now'>What we have now</h2>
<p>What are we burning to the ground, you ask? Well, a system of organization that ignores the decentralized world we built out of it.
We build software in a centralized manner. It has one blessed location where it exists, the pieces used to build it (libraries, frameworks) are all built in a centralized manner and exist in generally one place, and we generally hold a relationship between a set of a few people as being in control of that code (and we bless them, perhaps religiously in some cases.)</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/djehuty-technical/apocalypse.jpg' title='' alt='Ok. It's not *that* bad, but we can do better. [1]' /><br /><div class='caption'>Ok. It's not *that* bad, but we can do better. [1]</div></div><p></p>

<p>This has resulted in a tolerable, yet inefficient ecosystem where we tend to rewrite instead of reuse.
This is due to spirited debates about abstractions, expression, and simply how likable a set of people are.
This system inherits the lack of diversity of its whole and by being so centralized to ego, it leaves out a rather
large yet invisible section of humanity.</p>

<p>You may disagree with the prior paragraph since it may come across too harsh. However, ask yourself if this model of development of projects, especially in a world of opensource ideals and an increasingly decentralized network, is really appropriate, efficient, or if anything could be better if designed with these technical considerations in mind. My argument hinges on it being both a technical <strong>and</strong> social gain.</p>
<h2 id='a_new_infrastructure'>A new infrastructure</h2>
<p>I have <a  href='/posts/apples' title=''>discussed previously</a> the lack of a distinction between computation and abstraction. Our new infrastructure must promote computation first. How we invoke a behavior should simply be by telling the machine to perform that behavior. Anything beyond that (the human component) is beyond the scope.</p>

<p>What we end up with is a list of behaviors. Each behavior has a common name that is used to invoke it. Each behavior has a well-defined input and will have a well-defined output. Each behavior has a specification that details how the computation should take place; it is a description of input and output. I discuss this component of the infrastructure in <a  href='/posts/infrastructure' title=''>more detail here</a>.</p>

<p>Beyond these basic descriptions of computation, at the software level, we have something on either side of this thin interface. On the left, is the implementation of the behavior. This can be a piece of code, in whatever language, that takes the input and yields the appropriate output. It could also be a piece of hardware that upholds the specification. In either respect, the implementation is a black box, and regardless of how a behavior is implemented, it is compared against the specification and all other implementations.</p>

<p>On the right of the interface is the abstraction. In this area we have the parts that are for human consumption. These are languages that glue together behaviors to produce something meaningful, artistic, useful, etc. They could be frameworks that make rapid development possible. Some programming languages are more meaningful on this side of the interface, such as scripting and/or dynamic languages.</p>

<p>This is the software component. It is driven by the notion that we select code by what it does, not by what it is called, what language it is written in, or who maintains it. We keep the benefits of abstractions, but they no longer inhibit or obscure performance gains in other parts of the system. I will continue to strengthen these points.</p>
<h2 id='the_hardware'>The hardware</h2>
<p>Regarding the left side of the interface which implements well-defined behavior, it is interesting that since such an implementation is a black box, it may be implemented as hardware. We live in a world where 3d-printed hardware is increasingly available. Now, we can find a bottleneck in our software and have our computers print a hardware implementation to solve the performance issue. We can plug in a hardware solution and have it transparently affect any software which uses that interface immediately.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/djehuty-technical/printer.jpg' title='' alt='Although not feasible yet, printable conductive gels exist and could make circuit printing available in the home. [2]' /><br /><div class='caption'>Although not feasible yet, <a href="http://news.stanford.edu/news/2012/june/printable-electrical-hydrogel-062712.html">printable conductive gels</a> exist and could make circuit printing available in the home. [2]</div></div><p></p>

<p>By using this software infrastructure, we make 3d-printed hardware more meaningful and easier to use for less technical users. We allow anybody with hardware knowledge the ability to contribute to opensource hardware communities by giving them the ability to easily solve any computational problem at any granularity (write a hardware implementation for a yaml parser, or maybe just write a hardware tokenizer, hardware string routines... you decide.) All in all, we will promote the much needed involvement from the electrical/computer/etc engineers and makers.</p>
<h2 id='the_network'>The network</h2>
<p>We currently make use of a huge, barely centralized network of networks we call the internet. This network currently allows you to own a name &#39;davewilkinsonii.com&#39; or &#39;github.com&#39; and then use that name to map resources: &#39;davewilkinsonii.com/posts/djehuty&#39; and &#39;github.com/wilkie/blog&#39;. We then communicate using well-defined methods in order to retrieve and make sense of those resources: &#39;http&#39; or &#39;git&#39; respectively.</p>

<p>Alright, say what you want about hardware and copyright, but the network implications here are the real political meat and bones. We want to provide these elements of computation without the interference of a central authority, government, or malicious organization. We want to ensure both the availability and integrity of the code. We may need to devise a new network infrastructure to support this in a minimal fashion, or craft it out of the parts we already have, namely the internet and world wide web as it is now.</p>

<p>Frankly, the internet as it stands strengthens the argument for this style of encapsulation of interfaces.
It supports a decentralized model where we can ask a question and get an answer. &quot;I need a way to compute a sort of a list of numbers&quot; can retrieve an implementation for quicksort, or maybe on another day will retrieve an implementation of insertion sort. Who knows. All we have to have here, as a basic minimum, is the ability to get <em>any implementation</em> that fulfills the specification, of which you retrieve once.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/djehuty-technical/peer-to-peer.png' title='' alt='A peer-to-peer network should be the base model of the infrastructure. [3]' /><br /><div class='caption'>A peer-to-peer network should be the base model of the infrastructure. [3]</div></div><p></p>

<p>Now, with clever use of DNS and frontend servers, we can have a single name resolve to different resources. This is typically done to route resources to the nearest server geographically in order to balance demand and increase responsiveness on popular websites. However, here, we want to get an implementation of a behavior. We can co-opt the internet to get this behavior the same way that bittorrent does in order to create a network without an owner or central authority.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, we can ask for an implementation and get one from a server in belize or our neighbor at the coffee shop, along with any technical data about how performant that implementation is. We can get many implementations and compare them and publish our data as well. What we want to create is something a bit more flexible than the web, but still within its foundational spirit, more like a network of mesh networks.</p>

<p>To sum up, unlike the normal use of the internet and hypermedia, we want to retrieve something that fulfills a behavior through a specification, not retrieve something of a particular name. This network is peer-driven and content-driven, although the specifics of how this would be done are beyond my expertise.</p>
<h2 id='technical_merit'>Technical merit</h2>
<p>Through the design and implementation of such an infrastructure, we can achieve many technical goals that are far more difficult otherwise. This is due to the emphasis on benchmarking and scientific measurement over human expression and abstractions.</p>
<h3 id='science_to_automate_optimizations_of_software_structure'>Science to automate optimizations of software structure</h3>
<p>This type of design will allow for competing implementations based upon facts related to performance and separates those concerns from how computation is expressed, which is relegated to higher level languages. This will promote code reuse across all languages and remove the need for a <em>standard library</em> that reimplements basic functionality other languages already have. New languages can be created and supported by an existing wealth of code, and only need to bind to these interfaces to be able to use it. Languages may want to provide better abstractions and perhaps push policies to allow for better expression or analysis, but can do so around the code that already exists instead of rewriting everything.</p>
<h3 id='availability_of_code'>Availability of code</h3>
<p>Since useful code will exist on many machines, implementations can be retrieved from a great number of sources. This improves availability of code and ensures that code cannot be removed (<a  href='#social_merit' title=''>see social merit</a>.) Machines may also pass performance details and metrics that it has gathered among the machines it knows to help the destination machine make decisions about which implementation to use. We can effectively crowdsource science about our code. Detailing this type of information would be a big win in optimizing the entire code base on our machines toward specific performance goals. Also, no authority would have a practical method of deleting code or subjecting laws against its use or proliferation.</p>
<h3 id='increased_feasibility_of_hardware_printing'>Increased feasibility of hardware printing</h3>
<p>This infrastructure, as mentioned, promotes hardware implementations that may increase the performance in terms of speed and possibly power when the machine suggests that it could benefit. Hardware implementations will abide by the same specifications as software components, and can therefore be tested against them in already existing applications. This should promote hardware as an optimization of software which in turn can create hardware with less bugs and have the hardware become useful immediately after production. Drivers for hardware are no longer platform specific as they are simply implementations of behavior, and operating system behaviors are also described in the infrastructure.</p>
<h2 id='social_merit'>Social merit</h2>
<p>Computation is important to all people. There are cultures that could benefit from equal access to technology and computation. With this infrastructure, society serves to benefit due to the promotion of solutions without attribution and an ecosystem where code propagates across the world without interference.</p>
<h3 id='ubiquitous_code'>Ubiquitous code</h3>
<p>By greatly modularizing code, implementations can exist anywhere. This has a beneficial side-effect: code is much harder to censor or delete. You can build a dependency graph for any application and simply ask any machine in the world for some code that implements those behaviors. Any implementation can be retrieved and then tested for correctness. We can get code reliably from our neighbors, for instance. This better ensures that a single centralized location for code is not the norm, and therefore reduces the ability for centralized authorities to remove or restrict access to computation. Useful code will exist on many machines, and these implementations can be retrieved (along with performance information, <a  href='#technical_merit' title=''>see technical merit</a>) from any machine in a network.</p>
<h3 id='lower_cost_of_entry'>Lower cost of entry</h3>
<p>This has another benefit of greatly reducing the cost of entry for using technology. We only need to provide simple hardware with network capability, network driver, and a simple buildtool and dependency grapher to determine what code we need to build the rest of the system. From there it can acquire that code, verify its correctness, and compile the rest of the system. This means 3d-printed hardware can become more feasible as it would have less software requirements out of the box to get it working and deployed on a large scale. As mentioned, we require a better, more specialized network infrastructure to support the peer-to-peer nature of the system where new (untrusted) nodes can enter at anytime, perhaps toward a mesh network or some hybrid mesh-network and typical centralized structure. The social benefit of not using the internet is that we can minimize the technical barrier of entry to create a new system.</p>
<h3 id='machines_that_build_themselves'>Machines that build themselves</h3>
<p>The prospect of hardware printing means that such solutions are potentially available to all people who can manufacture a 3d-printer, or acquire one that can print itself. At the end of the day, we can provide a minimal subset of components that can be used to generate the rest of the machine from information in the network. This should reduce the physical costs of the machine. Upgrades to the machine would be as easy as acquiring the machine, and furthermore would be available to all through the network. Hence, this infrastructure, when implemented at all three components (software, hardware, and network) create a sustainable computational platform for all of humanity and firmly place the power of computation freely in the hands of the people.</p>
<h3 id='references'>References</h3><ol><a id='ref_1'></a><li>Artist&#39;s depiction of apocalypse from <a  href='http://pierremassine.deviantart.com/art/Apocalypse-145369171' title=''>here</a>.
</li><a id='ref_2'></a><li>Discussion of affordable 3d printing <a  href='http://www.engadget.com/2012/09/26/form-1-delivers-high-end-3d-printing-for-an-affordable-price/' title=''>here</a>, which the image was taken.
</li><a id='ref_3'></a><li>The minimalistic image of a peer-to-peer network and a simple description of what that is can be found <a  href='http://www.freelan.org/' title=''>here</a>.
</li></ol>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/djehuty-technical</guid></item><item><title>The Antirez Principle</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/the-antirez-principle</link><description><![CDATA[<p>On Saturday, October 13th 2012, Salvatore Sanfilippo, also known as antirez,
an influential hacker who maintains redis, published a blog entry entitled
&quot;<a  href='http://oldblog.antirez.com/post/different-take-sexism-it.html' title=''>A different take on sexism in IT</a>.&quot;
It made its way onto <a  href='http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4648625' title=''>Hacker News</a>, and received, according to his own website, over 20,000 views.</p>

<p>This post received a divisive reaction on twitter leading Salvatore to quit the
social network <a  href='https://twitter.com/antirez/status/257618545410723840' title=''>altogether</a>.
However well-intentioned Salvatore may have believed himself to be, his post
on the topic of tech-related sexism has some major flaws. Shanley gives a
good rundown of his entry <a  href='http://blog.prettylittlestatemachine.com/blog/2012/10/14/antirez-on-sexism/' title=''>on her blog</a> as well.</p>

<p>I want to break down this article and explain the different fallacies of
his argument and also some strategies employed that create an illusion of
correctness and distract from contradictions in the rest of the article.
I&#39;ve added some comments in brackets to correct some of Salvatore&#39;s English
(he is not a native speaker) just for the benefit of easy reading.</p>

<hr>

<blockquote>
<p>More than ten years ago I started to understand that sexism in IT was not an easy topic. Talking with my female coworkers I discovered they were deeply upset and offended by other women that were too [read: found it] easy to ask for respect using sexism as a flag. At first I was a bit shocked about that, but then I realised how obvious it is. </p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id='anecdote_provides_epiphany'>Anecdote Provides Epiphany</h2>
<p>Salvatore starts out explaining that sexism is not an easy topic. He is correct, of course. The history of oppression of any kind is long and complicated.
However, he sidesteps this history by discussing his personal conversations with his female coworkers. He suggests that these women were offended at
the usage of sexism as a means of gaining undue respect.</p>

<p>This is the crux of his argument; that is, the problem statement. Women should not be getting special treatment on the terms of their gender. I want
to emphasize this. Everything else that is said relates to this idea: women are gaining too much. What does this mean? It suggests that he believes
oppression does not exist, because this is contradicted with the response to this supposed oppression leading to a gain for women.
The problem with this statement is that it presents a cause is effect argument which he expands upon later.</p>

<p>This argument is further unfounded since it makes exclusive use of an anecdote. An anecdote is a situation, and inherits any situational cause to its reported
effect. However, this serves to further hurt Salvatore&#39;s ability to empathize considering this anecdote is based on his observations of women, and thus uses this
as the genesis of his argument as a suggestion that he is relating what women want and what women feel. That is, that the argument that follows is an explanation
of how women see this issue, not just him.</p>

<hr>

<blockquote>
<p>As a woman you want respect because you are capable and smart. Not because you are a woman. </p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id='the_indisputable_claim'>The Indisputable Claim</h2>
<p>Salvatore then follows it with the goal. If this is achieved, the situational problem he discussed is eraticated. This is true since he is claiming
essentially that women are gaining unfairly, so equality based upon merit would solve this unfairness. Note, however, it is the same solution
to the problem where women are being oppressed and discriminated against based solely on gender, such as the very real <a  href='http://www.iwpr.org/publications/pubs/the-gender-wage-gap-2009' title=''>gender wage gap</a>.</p>

<p>The usage of an indisputable claim in a debate or argument is a classic technique. You suggest something that your opponent must agree with
so that an attack on a side-issue or side-claim can be called out as an attack on the shared goal. This goal of equality without regard to
gender on issues such as intelligence and creativity is the general goal of feminism. Therefore, he has created an obstacle (the means of
building a strawman) for those that disagree with his assertions of the allotment of power and oppression.</p>

<p>It is such a powerful technique that he received support from women based solely on this one statement. New York Times Assistant Editor
Jacqui Maher gives <a  href='https://twitter.com/jacqui/status/257479804570439680' title=''>her support</a> by quoting this phrase exactly and nothing more. This
is quickly retweeted by Salvatore. It is unclear whether or not Jacqui supports the rest of the article, and she has not answered the questions
<a  href='https://twitter.com/wilkieii/status/257283943714394112' title=''>I have sent her</a> asking for elaboration, but it stands to reason that an editor would not skim, and that she supports the entire text.</p>

<hr>

<blockquote>
<p>In the course of my life I started to develop an higher and higher intolerance for topics like politically correctness and protection of minorities unless this was clearly put in general terms. If you are an human being you need to be respected because you deserve respect like any other. I don&#39;t care if you are black, white, yellow or woman, you are an individual. </p>

<p>Similarly, I will not care who you are if you do something silly at work. Nothing is more offensive for you than me being too easy with you because you are part of some minority. This is, basically, a masked form of reverse-sexism, and is deeply offensive. This is what my female coworkers meant when they were so upset against other women talking about sexism too easily. </p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id='blaming_the_victims'>Blaming the Victims</h2>
<p>This is where the proposed argument made in the first paragraph becomes explicit. Salvatore suggests the the protection against discrimination is
overzealous political correctness. He makes the notion that people deserve equal respect, a noble mindset, and again asserts that no special treatment
should be considered, even with regard to protection, for any attribute that doesn&#39;t relate to merit.</p>

<p>He then, in the second paragraph above, suggests that it is offensive to women for anyone to abide by this political correctness. The implication is
that women do not need protection and that women can overcome any social obstacles in their way on their own. He suggests that to do the contrary and
provide some measure of protection against discrimination and policing oppression and privilege in this situation would amount to &quot;reverse-sexism,&quot;
where he relates to the original anecdote being a situation where a woman oppresses others (including women) through the undue respect she gained.</p>

<p>This amounts to blaming the victims, and furthermore it puts the burden of the argument on those individuals who are oppressed and have experienced
sexism in the tech field to prove that they do not gain from it. Also, by placing the burden of argument on these individuals, it attempts to
illegitimize the progress women and minorities have made.</p>

<hr>

<blockquote>
<p>In general if there is a problem at the work place between individual A and B, I think it is always an error to talk about sexism, even when the root cause is some asshole not respecting you because you are a woman. Instead the problem should be addressed in a sexual agnostic way. Why is A not payed [read: paid] like B even if they have similar responsibilities and tasks? Why A is not respected by B as she deservers as an individual?</p>

<p>Trying to protect women in tech since they are women is like moving a cultural problem (the sexism) into an individual domain. A woman in tech has nothing less than a male in tech, as such does not need special care or protection. She needs to be respected as everybody else. </p>

<p>Another naive way to consider the problem is to think that sexism is a state of mind of men. Actually the problem is more complex than that, and a lot of women don&#39;t consider themselves or other women as capable as men.</p>

<p>Blog posts about this topic that try to make people aware of sexism or try to send the message &quot;we should be all kind so that women will feel great in our industry&quot; are not the solution, nor to stress politically correctness is going to help at all. As a proof in the United States where politically correctness and protection of minority is a topic always over-discussed, the condition of women is worse than in North Europe, where such an obsession does not exist. </p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id='effect_is_cause'>Effect is Cause</h2>
<p>Here, Salvatore talks about how to better handle claims of sexism in an environment that should promote merit. He suggests here that
we should not look at the claim of sexism as being about gender oppression, but rather about why there is a lack of equality when
a woman and a man are effectively equal.</p>

<p>Again, this is a shared goal. It is obviously desired to end gender oppression to end biases made based upon gender. However, Salvatore&#39;s main
claim in this section is that by highlighting sexism as being about gender oppression, we are actually causing such oppression to take
place. This is a very typical false-cause argument used in these discussions by anti-political-correctness proponents.</p>

<p>In the end, however, he suggests that we do not look at gender at all to address issues related to gender. This is a bizarre contradiction. It
also suggests that the only way to combat sexism is to erase gender, which sidesteps the notion that gender is a component of an individual
that should be able to exist alongside other attributes of a person&#39;s identity, such as strength, character, skill, and intelligence.</p>

<hr>

<blockquote>
<p>It&#39;s silly to try to protect all the minorities [simply] because they are minorities. We should protect individuals as they have equal dignity, without resort[ing] to sex, race, and other discriminatory attributes.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He then contributes a conclusion that sums up the idea that any attempt to curb the discrimination, or affirmative action, is immoral and itself discrimination.
This completely ties together his theme of the post.</p>
<h2 id='my_response'>My Response</h2>
<p>I do not agree with the theme that Salvatore hinges his argument upon nor his general conclusion.
I agree with the goal but not the propositions of the argument. Remember, the goal
is to provide an environment where gender is not considered when measuring merit. Everybody should agree with this.</p>

<p>I disagree with the idea that discussing the topic of sexism leads to oppression, and I disagree with the idea that political
correctness has led to a state where it is common for women to profit undue respect. There have been centuries of oppression based
upon not only sex and gender, but race and sexual orientation, even in a country as young as the United States, which will be
my focus here.</p>

<p>Anti-political-correctness advocates normally stress the rise of political correctness as a trend that is slowly eradicating the
right to free speech. For Salvatore&#39;s comments about the nature of oppression correlating to the political correctness to be true,
PC must have come first to create the cause-effect relationship he suggests. Common belief is that this relationship is reversed, and
PC is caused by the acknowledgement of oppression.</p>

<p>However, the oppression of women is historically, and commonly known. Women&#39;s Suffrage was an issue throughout many nations.
Specifically, in the US, suffrage was given and taken away several times by states. Only by
the year 1919 through 1920 did federal support and a <a  href='http://www.archives.gov/education/lessons/woman-suffrage/ratification-tn.html' title=''>constitutional amendment</a> provide the right to vote to all women regardless
of land ownership or resident state (although minority women were still discriminated against in this area for years to come.) It wasn&#39;t until around 1958, however, until all states officially ratified the amendment.
Gender gap statistics give factual insight into the effect of social oppression, and have seen <a  href='http://www3.weforum.org/docs/WEF_GenderGap_Report_2011.pdf' title=''>worldwide positive progress</a> alongside this presumed trend
in political correctness, although are still far from equal. Therefore, the oppression of women (I&#39;ve only highlighted one example of many!) predates the notion of political correctness
and even within the environment of political correctness, the gender gap has gotten better, not worse. We are indeed, I am happy to report, making some movement toward equality.
Talking about these issues does <em>not</em> interfere with progress, which should sound completely obvious.</p>

<p>As for systemic oppression, it affects all genders and it is a subconscious process. That is, in our society there exists an ingrained bias toward one gender over another and this bias affects women as well as men. An experiment by New York University psychology
professor Madeline Heilman showed that a male leader seemed <a  href='http://www.theage.com.au/national/how-the-sex-bias-prevails-20100514-v4mv.html' title=''>more likeable than a female leader</a>
when the descriptions and facts presented for them were exactly the same. This supports the biases that cause the lack of female CEOs of fortune 500 companies, which only as of 2012 <a  href='http://postcards.blogs.fortune.cnn.com/2012/07/18/fortune-500-women-ceos-2/' title=''>hit a record 4%</a> with only 1 representing the top ten. The lack of women holding higher positions is a force that could cause the gender gap, as these positions would generally pay more and gain access to more opportunities.</p>

<p>How about access to skilled labor? Salvatore&#39;s argument is rooted in the technology industry. This is a field wrought with problems
of gender discrimination. Sapna Cheryan, professor of psychology specializing in cultural stereotypes at the University of Washington, wrote
a paper published in the Journal of Personality and Social Psychology thoroughly entitled &quot;Why do women consider a future in computer science to a lesser extent than men?&quot;
In this paper she discusses the effects of the <em>stereotype threat</em> where the false ideas and perceptions of the computer scientist and
the field itself correlate to the disinterest women have in pursuing that career. Sapna gives an excelent <a  href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TYwI-qM20x4' title=''>TEDx talk</a> on the subject.</p>

<p>This idea is supported by several other studies such as Spencer, Steele, and Quinn&#39;s
<a  href='http://www.leedsmet.ac.uk/carnegie/learning_resources/LAW_PGCHE/SteeleandQuinnStereotypeThreat.pdf' title=''>&quot;Stereotype Threat and Women&#39;s Math Performance.&quot;</a>
In this study, they have participants take a difficult math test. In one case, they reproduced an earlier result of women performing worse than men on
difficult tests, but perform equally well on easy ones. Then, they take a similar group and told them that there were no gender differences to be
expected, which defies the stereotype. The women in this group do equally well as the men. The conclusion is that it is the presence of the stereotype
that affects their performance. All in all, the stereotype of the geek promotes disinterest, which prevents women from ever considering the tech
field. If they do, then the stereotype that provides the notion that women
are worse at math and science actually causes women to perform worse in the educational settings, and may cause them to drop out.</p>

<p>These are issues worth discussing. There is ingrained, systemic oppression that cause these issues. They will not be solved by ignoring these
facts. We cannot, as Salvatore suggests, simply close our eyes and base everything on merit, because we will be betrayed by our biases. We cannot
promote more diversity if the conditions of the field and the perceptions of our field to others are not equipped to deal with combatting these
stereotypes.</p>

<p>We must provide solutions, and that solution, in a broad brush stroke, is education. We must push gender equality in math and science as early
<a  href='http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2011/03/110314091642.htm' title=''>as second grade</a>, which includes introductions to computer science. We must
offer our support to mentorships that are inclusive to women and minorities such as <a  href='http://www.cs.pitt.edu/tli/' title=''>TLI</a>, <a  href='http://railsgirls.com/' title=''>RailsGirls</a>,
<a  href='http://girldevelopit.com/' title=''>GirlDevelopIt</a> along with many others. Yes, they select by gender and age. This is ok. Early education can
eliminate the stereotype threat, but for those of us living in this society, the stereotype threat can lead to a <a  href='http://tigger.uic.edu/~mcmpsych/documents/MurphySteeleGross2007.pdf' title=''>lack of belonging</a>
in groups that underrepresent women.</p>

<p>We are not creating these groups because women need the extra support and consideration. On the contrary, we create and support these groups because they
prove the obvious <em>without</em> erasing one&#39;s gender: that women are equal to men. They are not without their own problems, but they are a solution to a severe issue that I&#39;m sure
people 100 years ago expected us to solve by now. We don&#39;t discuss these issues because we are &quot;whiners&quot;, &quot;complainers&quot;, &quot;white knights&quot;, or &quot;political correctness
police.&quot; We bring these things up over and over again because these <a  href='http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Category:Incidents' title=''>issues simply keep occurring</a>, because the
facts support our claim, and because we know that if the issue is dropped or becomes less visible, it will not be solved. And because, at the end of the day, women <em>indeed</em> deserve respect because they are capable and smart, and furthermore
they deserve respect because they are women.</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/the-antirez-principle</guid></item><item><title>An Infrastructure to Promote Sustainable Software</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/infrastructure</link><description><![CDATA[<p>We have long promoted the idea of the re-usability of our code. After an era of writing for our machines instead of ourselves, we discovered that human literacy was preferred over performance. From this notion, we developed higher level languages that started to abstract and even completely obscure the underlying machine. A beautiful era emerged where the Turing machine was our model, and humans our audience.</p>

<p>However, these methods of human expression are not compatible. Although they all express and run upon the same theoretical basis, they cannot collaborate effectively. This is due, ironically, to the constraints set upon the languages at the machine level. For instance, {Rust, D, Java} implies a garbage collector to allow object expressions that ignore allocations and to better analyze the lifetimes of these objects. When the language constrains the type of garbage collector policy, this constrains the languages that can be used together.</p>

<p>However, it is true that these constraints are not necessary to be Turing complete. For instance, languages that force constraints can still utilize languages that make less (or no) constraints. This is why C is currently preferred for optimizations across languages. We can do slightly better than C, but we must respect the aspects (or lack thereof?) of C that have made it so ubiquitous.</p>

<p>Frankly, computation is simply the transform of information from one phase to another dependent on state. This is the model of the Turing Machine. Such a transformation is hereby called a <em>behavior</em>. If behaviors are cleanly described and specified without interpretation, they can be used within any language that has the means to describe that they wish a behavior to be used.</p>
<h2 id='we_must_have_a_language_that_describes_behavior_void_of_policy'>We must have a language that describes behavior void of policy</h2>
<p>In order to cleanly reuse code, we must reuse it at the behavioral level. There shall be no policy about allocations, threading, or architecture unless this is necessary to define the behavior. The implementations of behavior may choose a policy when it benefits that implementation. Behaviors may depend on policy when they are behaviors related to policy (such as describing a memory pool system or threading library in terms of behaviors.)</p>

<p>Only basic language capabilities to describe a name, a set of inputs, and a set of outputs are necessary. Since computation is a mapping of inputs to outputs, providing mutability constraints to both inputs and outputs becomes necessary, including any defined data types such as structs. Generally, inputs will be immutable, but this must be described by the behavior and thus by the language that one writes the interface to the behavior.</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>function String.concat(immutable char[] input) : char[]

function MutableString.concat(immutable char[] input) : void
</code></pre><h2 id='behaviors_are_an_interface_and_a_specification'>Behaviors are an interface and a specification</h2>
<p>To thoroughly describe how computation is performed, you must describe both the interface and the mapping of inputs to outputs as invariants. There must be a single way to invoke the behavior, and a determined outcome described by a formal model (and informally enforced through a set of tests.) The model is hereby called the <em>specification</em>.</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>function Array.sort(immutable int[] input) : int[]

describe Array.sort {
  it &quot;sorts in ascending order&quot; {
    // Randomly generate a list
    // Go through list and check that each item is &lt;= the prior
    // Test gives us a certain amount of confidence that the behavior is
    //  performed by an implementation.
  }
}
</code></pre><h2 id='implementations_of_behavior_must_be_flexible'>Implementations of behavior must be flexible</h2>
<p>Implementing a behavior (such as sorting a list of non-unique items) can be done various ways. Therefore, since performance of a behavior relates to the distributions of its input, the agent choosing how a behavior is performed should have the ability to switch the implementation. Since the behavior does not change, neither does the interface to invoke that behavior. Therefore, nothing must change in the higher level expression to perform the behavior.</p>

<p>The above description of behavior for the Array.sort specifies the outcome of the computation. Notice, however, that it does not assert performance goals such as wall-time, energy-usage or memory-usage as a factor of the input. That is the responsibility of the implementation. And many implementations could satisfy the interface and the specification.</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>function Array.sort(immutable int[] input) : int[] {
  // Insertion sort
}

function Array.sort(immutable int[] input) : int[] {
  // Quick sort
}

function Array.sort(immutable int[] input) : int[] {
  // Quick sort + Insertion sort
}
</code></pre>
<p>Which one of these implementations is best? Who knows. Use all of them, or perform a benchmark to determine which is the best to use, and link it in. This can be done over a period of time where the program can rerun benchmarks and switch the implementations, or done at the developer&#39;s discretion. However, it does not interfere with the expression of &#39;performing a sort&#39; which means the application code does not need to change to switch the implementation.</p>

<p>We don&#39;t need to allow multiple implementations to be defined in our languages. We will assume that implementations are largely unknown to begin with. You &#39;discover&#39; them over time, through other machines, though people, through applications that beg for a particular one. We discover how good they are through a community: the machine next to you swears that its applications run using 40% less energy with this implementation instead of the one you are using. We can do these things once we start to respect behavioral definitions.</p>
<h2 id='technical_merit'>Technical merit</h2>
<p>This type of design will allow for competing implementations based upon facts related to performance and separates those concerns from how computation is expressed, which is relegated to higher level languages. This will promote code reuse across all languages and remove the need for a <em>standard library</em> that reimplements basic functionality other languages already have. New languages can be created and supported by an existing wealth of code, and only need to bind to these interfaces to be able to use it. Languages may want to provide better abstractions and perhaps push policies to allow for better expression or analysis, but can do so around the code that already exists instead of rewriting everything.</p>

<p>Since useful code will exist on many machines, implementations can be retrieved from a great number of sources. This improves availability of code and ensures that code cannot be removed (<a  href='#social_merit' title=''>see social merit</a>.) Machines may also pass performance details and metrics that it has gathered among the machines it knows to help the destination machine make decisions about which implementation to use. We can effectively crowdsource science about our code. Detailing this type of information would be a big win in optimizing the entire code base on our machines toward specific performance goals.</p>
<h2 id='social_merit'>Social merit</h2>
<p>By greatly modularizing code, implementations can exist anywhere. This has a beneficial side-effect: code is much harder to censor or delete. You can build a dependency graph for any application and simply ask any machine in the world for some code that implements those behaviors. Any implementation can be retrieved and then tested for correctness. We can get code reliably from our neighbors, for instance. This better ensures that a single centralized location for code is not the norm, and therefore reduces the ability for centralized authorities to remove or restrict access to computation. Useful code will exist on many machines, and these implementations can be retrieved (along with performance information, <a  href='#technical_merit' title=''>see technical merit</a>) from any machine in a network.</p>

<p>This has another benefit of greatly reducing the cost of entry for using technology. We only need to provide simple hardware with network capability, network driver, and a simple buildtool and dependency grapher to determine what code we need to build the rest of the system. From there it can acquire that code, verify its correctness, and compile the rest of the system. This means 3d-printed hardware can become more feasible as it would have less software requirements out of the box to get it working and deployed on a large scale. We may require a better network infrastructure to support the peer-to-peer nature of the system where new (untrusted) nodes can enter at anytime, perhaps toward a mesh network or some hybrid mesh-network and typical centralized structure.</p>

<p>I must defer to the hardware and network communities for their input, as it is not my area of expertise.</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/infrastructure</guid></item><item><title>Coding Naturally: How to Achieve Sustainable Software</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/apples</link><description><![CDATA[<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/apples/corgi.png' title='' alt='Corgi wants to be tall. [1]' /><br /><div class='caption'>Corgi wants to be tall. [1]</div></div><p></p>

<p>Here is a <a  href='https://imgur.com/r/corgi' title=''>corgi</a>. It&#39;s a puppy. And it is the absolute cutest thing. Ever. I&#39;m only slightly pandering.
But seriously, puppies are far superior to kittens. Dogs are more loyal than cats. I&#39;m not sure why the
internet has given cats so much attention. They suck.</p>
<h2 id='which_is_better_'>Which is better?</h2>
<p>Alright. I may be biased. This happens. Throughout our lives we very often find ourselves in the situation where we are presented two items and
expected to choose between them. So much so, that no matter how much we actually know about something, we
have decided ourselves experts.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/apples/apples.png' title='' alt='A braeburn and a pippin, which is better?' /><br /><div class='caption'>A braeburn and a pippin, which is better?</div></div><p></p>

<p>Don&#39;t act all high-and-mighty. Look, we all know at the grocery store in the
produce section, you, like everybody else, are there squeezing all of the fruit. What exactly are you
looking for? What makes one apple better than the other?</p>

<p>We look at the color, the shininess and luster, the size, and the smoothness. Why? Because we believe these
to be all great indicators of the quality of taste. They are all qualities that we see and perhaps feel.
However, are these the qualities of a great apple? It is a matter of perspective.</p>
<h2 id='what_is_an_apple_'>What is an apple?</h2>
<p>The attributes of an apple which we find pleasing are not indicative of what makes a great apple. These
traits do not concern the apple and its role and its function. The perception of an apple with respect to
these qualities ignores what an apple actually is. We just want to eat them.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/apples/apples_full_small.png' title='' alt='Taking a step back, how different can they be? [2]' /><br /><div class='caption'>Taking a step back, how different can they be? [2]</div></div><p></p>

<p>However, an apple, being a fruit and a <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pome' title=''>pome</a>, is a container for seeds. They
are designed to perform one function: <em>to create new trees</em>. If you start to look at the bigger picture,
the differences among the apples become meaningless. Shininess does not make one apple a better container than
another.</p>

<p>All of those inconsequential features we tend to look at are very much masking what is truly important, which
is the seed. These seeds are fundamentally the same in all apples and serve the same purpose and do so equally
well regardless of outer shell and presentation.</p>
<h2 id='learning_from_nature'>Learning from Nature</h2>
<p>In the software and engineering world, the concept of discussing irrelevant details that do not pertain to the
function of a system is called <em>bikeshedding</em>. That is, nobody argues over the function of the bike shed but
rather insist on its color.</p>

<p>In the software world, such discussion is only avoidable if we separate human opinion from computation, which is based upon fact. In
other words, if it were clear where the computation ended and the abstractions began, we could argue about the
expressive aspects of the code since changing them does not impact the choices on how the behavior is implemented.
In fact, it is the opposite, we argue precisely because we cannot see the line between computation and abstraction.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/apples/apples_full_smallest.png' title='' alt='Can the number of apples in the wild become overwhelming?' /><br /><div class='caption'>Can the number of apples in the wild become overwhelming?</div></div><p></p>

<p>That is, in the case of the apple, there is always some seed that is fundamentally the same in every argument. There
is a level where you cannot argue against the behavior of some functionality. Array sort <em>must</em> take some set of data
and arrange it <em>some well-defined</em> way. How you sort the array, well.</p>

<p>If we again consider the apple, we would have seeds and skins. To make the metaphor a bit more concrete: <em>Seeds</em> would be 
strictly computation. This is code that
is written for performance and behavior. Its interface is unchangeable and well-known. You cannot argue about
the interface without making factual comparisons about performance or correctness. You must
prove you are correct with a metric or test.</p>

<p>Then you have the <em>skin</em>, or your abstraction layer. It is simply a language that maps expressions to the interface of the seed.
Since the seeds are well-known, many competing skins can exist. Since the interface is strict, many seeds can exist as well.
Both sides of the interface become interchangeable. And thus, bikeshedding becomes irrelevant to providing computation
since anyone can implement
a new skin without interfering with others.</p>

<p>If competing technologies would standardize to an interface (create a seed), then we could use either or both depending
on our needs without any effort. We could use the abstraction of one with the implementation of the other, in fact. I call
this <em>sustainable design</em>.</p>
<h2 id='sustainable_design'>Sustainable Design</h2>
<p>To promote sustainable design, a software developer must consider the line drawn between expressing behavior and allowing
human expression through abstraction. To transform existing projects, collaboration between competitors (odd concept, eh?)
to define a seed is necessary. For instance, the back-ends for QT and GTK could be consolidated into a new project which implement
the same interface (seed) and then QT and GTK become the abstractions (skins) around it. In this case you could say C and C++ are then the
abstractions we choose. That&#39;s fine. In this world, the languages we choose are to better allow us to use existing code and get applications
written. We do not inherit a policy or a set of standard libraries that may or may not work well.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/apples/apples_drawing.svg' title='' alt='Behaviors are what we care about in the end.' /><br /><div class='caption'>Behaviors are what we care about in the end.</div></div><p></p>

<p>To provide such a design when writing new projects, write them as libraries with functions that are very specifically tied to behavior. This way, alternative
implementations may exist. Use abstractions in a separate layer (create that skin with all the luster you want) that makes using the library cleaner. You benefit
by allowing for better experimentation with new abstractions while isolating core behaviors. You also gain the audience of many languages.
You also benefit from a much easier and more intuitive ability to refactor implementations while isolating them from their abstractions. To do this, simply
reimplement the interface and link in the new code.</p>

<p>If you are writing a library, determine if prior work exists and implement your library using that interface (make use of an existing seed.) You will gain quick
adoption by being able to assert facts about performance gains over existing implementations, while also being able to be
quickly used by existing programs that already make use of the other implementations. If you are writing an abstraction, you can leverage
existing implementations and focus only on refining the language (implement for humans without hindering performance facts.) Existing programs may not easily adopt your new abstraction,
but they do not need to in order to benefit from performance improvements. When you write abstractions, you are worried about new, that is non-existing, programs.</p>

<p>Once we have such modularity in place, we can write an infrastructure that manages the code. It can do objective analysis on whatever
benchmarks are deemed important and throw out code that doesn&#39;t perform and replace it with same random implementation that fares well.
This system will push good implementations over the bad and can even collectively rate them among machines. Code can be verified as
working before it is used to ensure bugs are limited. You as a developer may develop with one module, but in the future, without your
awareness, a bug was caught, patched, and automatically retrieved to build your software. Fantastic.</p>

<p>For an introduction to the language we need to describe behaviors, <a  href='/posts/infrastructure' title=''>read on</a>.</p>
<h3 id='references'>References</h3><ol><a id='ref_1'></a><li>Corgi picture adorably used from <a  href='http://www.coloradocorgi.org' title=''>here</a>.
</li><a id='ref_2'></a><li>Pictures shamelessly used from <a  href='http://www.foodsubs.com/Apples.html' title=''>here</a>.
</li></ol>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/apples</guid></item><item><title>You want freedom? Build it.</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/you-want-freedom-build-it</link><description><![CDATA[<p>There has been <a  href='http://bytbox.net/blog/2012/08/leaving-github.html' title=''>many</a> a <a  href='http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4220353' title=''>debate</a> about the recent, somehow surprising discovery that github is a company with <a  href='http://peter.a16z.com/2012/07/09/software-eats-software-development/' title=''>interests</a> that are perhaps beyond our own. Whatever. Honestly, github is replaceable. The real issue is the one we as developers, creatives, and people who like difficult problems should be talking about: WTF is a centralized website doing wrapping a distributed protocol?</p>
<h2 id='the_problem'>The Problem</h2>
<p>I propose a simple, real-world problem: make code as available as possible and ensure that it is correct when retrieved and from the source you desire it. You may give up confidentiality and consistency since this is <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_security' title=''>impos</a>-<a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CAP_theorem' title=''>sible</a> given our goal. Can you provide this with high probability that code cannot be destroyed permanently?</p>

<p>We want it quickly, so we shouldn&#39;t reinvent. Therefore, let&#39;s look at what we have.</p>
<h2 id='what_is_git'>What is Git</h2>
<p><a  href='http://git-scm.com/' title=''>Git</a> is a ridiculously simple protocol. The design is made up of blocks and bridges like most distributed systems. The blocks are commits and the bridges are simple links between them. Follow the bridges from any point, you get a snapshot of the codebase. Easy.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>In many ways you can just see git as a filesystem — it&#39;s content-addressable, and it has a notion of versioning, but I really really designed it coming at the problem from the viewpoint of a filesystem person (hey, kernels is what I do), and I actually have absolutely zero interest in creating a traditional SCM system.
<div class="citation">&mdash; <cite>Linus Torvalds, designer of git and Linux kernel, <a  href='http://marc.info/?l=linux-kernel&m=111314792424707' title=''>available</a></cite></div></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Git projects can be distributed anywhere. Either as a link to the git project through some sort of URI or by duplicating most or all of the structure on a separate system. Consistency is maintained through hashes serving as unique identifiers to target specific commits (when named, this is a code branch) and internal delta objects lighten the load of replication.</p>

<p>Git preserves the integrity of the code (it would be rather worthless if it didn&#39;t) with simple hashes and availability through manual replication. The point of a service that uses git would be to strengthen the availability and simply relax and fall in love with the parts that ensure integrity.</p>

<p>Too much hand waving for you? Sweet, read <a  href='http://ftp.newartisans.com/pub/git.from.bottom.up.pdf' title=''>Git from the bottom up</a>.</p>
<h2 id='what_is_github'>What is Github</h2>
<p><a  href='http://github.com' title=''>Github</a> is a centralized website. It serves to host a git project. It is centralized in that it promotes a culture where code is available on their servers and nowhere else. The fact that you <em>can</em> distribute your code easily on different sites is a property of <em>git</em>, not github. If their servers go down (and they <a  href='https://github.com/blog/744-today-s-outage' title=''>do</a>) then your code only exists locally in the common case where you do not manually replicate it.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>By orienting around people rather than repositories, GitHub has become the de facto social network for programmers
<div class="citation">&mdash; <cite>Peter Levine, affiliated with the $100 million backing of github, <a  href='http://peter.a16z.com/2012/07/09/software-eats-software-development/' title=''>available</a></cite></div></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Full disclosure: <a  href='https://github.com/wilkie' title=''>All</a> <a  href='https://github.com/hotsh' title=''>of</a> <a  href='https://github.com/xomboverlord' title=''>my</a> <a  href='https://github.com/djehuty' title=''>code</a> is hosted there because people expect it to be. That&#39;s not a very good reason. Github does not solve the given problem.</p>
<h2 id='why_should_we_be_mad_'>Why Should We Be Mad?</h2>
<p>The thing is... git allows us to have high availability and a known point of access. Hell, we can have known points of access to particular commits. If we replicate and go through a peer-to-peer system, we can have a known point of access to many points of access.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>[CS is] just such an amazing field, and it&#39;s changed the world, and we&#39;re just at the beginning of the change.
<div class="citation">&mdash; <cite>Frances E. Allen, compiler and systems researcher, Turing Award winner</cite></div></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yet... github makes the whole availability thing a bit more difficult in the general case. This should absolutely infuriate us. That&#39;s a backward step to solving the given problem. It is a lack of substantial progress. Should we accept the concept of <em>social coding</em> that github gives us even though it hinders or obscures the socially beneficial prospects of a distributed system? Can a diverse set of people use our code <em>because</em> github exists? Nothing prohibits this for <em>git</em>, but nothing promotes it either.</p>
<h2 id='what_is_a_federated_system'>What is a Federated System</h2>
<p>Let&#39;s discuss an alternative to the centralized autonomy that github provides. A <em>federated system</em> is one that is distributed but acts within a common ecosystem. For example, a federated version of twitter would consist of many separately maintained machines (perhaps one is maintained by you) each serving a website. Each server is responsible for a subset of the content, but access to all public content is shared equally and assumed.</p>

<p>A non-federated distributed system would simply be these machines communicating within some set of pipes. A user on one machine would be a user of that machine. You would have a subset of capabilities which are local to that machine. Users would be detached from the whole, but able to interact with users of other systems through a protocol.</p>

<p>For example, a user of a federated twitter system would be a user on all machines. No matter which machine you use, you would have the same functionality available to you (tweet, reply, direct message). If any one machine knows you exist, you will be seen as a user on that machine even though you physically <em>exist</em> on another. They might even announce you to neighboring systems or replicate your content. Conversely, you will use your machine to interact with others as though they are on your server.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Status.net exists to fulfill a need of a lot of people, both on the public web and private web, to have a microblogging server that they can control.
<div class="citation">&mdash; <cite>Evan Prodromou, founder of status.net and identi.ca, <a  href='http://www.building43.com/videos/2010/04/29/opening-up-microblogging-with-founder-of-status-net/' title=''>available</a></cite></div></p>
</blockquote>

<p>You may have used a federated system such as this thing called <em>email</em>.</p>

<p>Of course, the federated twitter exists. It is a solved problem. It is both <a  href='http://status.net' title=''>status.net</a> which powers <a  href='https://identi.ca' title=''>identi.ca</a> and <a  href='https://rstat.us' title=''>rstat.us</a>, which do indeed talk to each other and other entities.</p>

<p>You build federated systems on top of distributed ones. Federation is a subset. It allows one to contribute to a global view, but retain ownership, control, and integrity of their content.</p>
<h2 id='the_solution'>The Solution</h2>
<p>We need a system that promotes the features of git that are of both practical and social importance: availability and integrity. We need a system that does not allow code to be destroyed or censored. This is something github cannot do. Such a system is only possible through the exposing and leveraging of the distributed nature of git. A git repository is a shared view of a set of commits. A true web-based client of git is by nature already distributed.</p>

<p>To federate the system, all git repositories would be visible and accessible through any system. This could be done very much the way your twitter followers would be distributed leaving a system where all users interact equally. The origins of social interactions (notifications, messages, comments) would be abstracted as well. This is, of course, the same as twitter status updates. A federated twitter is a solved problem, as I stated. The protocol is <a  href='http://ostatus.org/sites/default/files/ostatus-1.0-draft-2-specification.html' title=''>OStatus</a>, replication is through <a  href='https://code.google.com/p/pubsubhubbub/' title=''>PuSH</a> and untrusted notifications are through <a  href='http://salmon-protocol.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/draft-panzer-salmon-00.html' title=''>salmon</a>. So we just need a <a  href='https://github.com/gitlabhq/gitlabhq/' title=''>git web client</a>. (Spoilers: we have one.)</p>

<p>Encouraging replication is fairly simple, but certainly second-iteration. I mean, replication is intuitive to git. Any local copy should be able to be pulled from in a peer-to-peer fashion. The commits are preserved (all history is linked) and have a point of access (hash) as a matter of design. So anybody that installs your code or forks it will be able to host it. Optional, of course, but cooperation can be incentivized. Peer-to-peer protocols are becoming rather commonplace already, for instance, in <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent#Software' title=''>video game patching</a> and package management, although typically not well-marketed perhaps due to a negative association with piracy. Using p2p here can ensure that one cannot locate all copies of code easily and therefore preserve them from accident or maliciousness.</p>

<p>Determining that the origin of some information is who you think it is, and furthermore that one&#39;s attribution can be ensured through private keys and self-hosted identity (through something like <a  href='http://code.google.com/p/webfinger/' title=''>webfinger</a>, Blaine Cook reminds me that it is encouraged to <a  href='http://blog.romeda.org/2011/03/private-webhooks-private-feeds.html' title=''>separate authenticity</a> and I&#39;ll add it is important to be able to self-host and control one&#39;s identity).</p>

<p>Put all of these in the same bowl. Mix. Enjoy.</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/you-want-freedom-build-it</guid></item><item><title>Who Am I?</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/who-am-i</link><description><![CDATA[<p>My life has not been perfect, prestine, or predictable. From youth to adulthood, I have not been what most would consider normal or everyday. I believe strongly in myself and I have spent a lot of effort meditating and reflecting upon my life. I generally understand where I come from.</p>

<p>I am a hacker and computer scientist. I am considered quite a heretic from the experts in my field. My mentors and idols have luckily convinced me to follow my heart. However, I need the help of many, and that burden upon you requires trust. So, I&#39;d like to have a conversation about who I am and what motivates me.</p>
<h2 id='my_father'>My Father</h2>
<p>In the beginning, I had it fairly good. In the past, my father was an alcoholic. Because of this, he did not get to raise my (half) brother and sister. That job went to my grandparents and the mother of my siblings. Eventually, in what can be seen as a tribute to my father&#39;s strength, he turned his life around. However, he traded one addiction for another, and as a result of his overworking, he did not get to raise me.</p>

<p>Currently, he has relapsed and is currently struggling to stay off the homeless front. He has support and is healthy, however, which is good. He has a non-cancerous tumor in his brain that causes his many medical issues, but as a veteran, he has excellent healthcare and services. He is not quite able to take care of himself anymore, and has never really been able to take care of me.</p>

<p>But, I said I had it good, right? My father successfully fulfilled his goal to put us in the upper middle class. We lived a good life. We had the two story house with the pool in the backyard. Yet, this was not his dream. When the opportunity to take over the family business presented itself, my father jumped. He quit his upper management job and uprooted my mother and my five year-old self from our suburban D.C. home to an old house in Johnstown, Pennsylvania.</p>
<h2 id='youth_and_code'>Youth and Code</h2>
<p>Although my family made some drastic changes, we were still doing quite well relative to most people. My family had security, money, and an upscale lifestyle. My father expanded our modest home to something twice the size. I had good friends. I was popular and social, as much as a 6 year-old could be, at least. I wonder, with some awe and fear, what my life would have been like--- who I would have become if my life had continued to follow that path.</p>

<p>I was introduced to code at around 6 years old with Basic, QBasic, and Visual Basic. It was a means of competition between me and my brother who is ten years older. Our competitions would consist of us writing a program called &quot;Change the Letters&quot; which demoed a technique that we had learned. The only rule was the program had to update the text in the title bar dynamically. We would go back and forth (incrementing the version number every time) trying to outdo the other. We wrote applications spanning from a simple calculator, to a simple renderer, to a word processor, to a media player. At some point, my brother asked me to code something for him. That&#39;s when I knew. I had won.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/who-am-i/qbasic.jpg' title='' alt='This doesn't call me names unless I tell it to.' /><br /><div class='caption'>This doesn't call me names unless I tell it to.</div></div><p></p>

<p>Meanwhile, my father kept attempting to live his dream of starting a restaurant. He started a sandwich shop called the &quot;Dilly Delly&quot; (Yep. That&#39;s what it is called. I just can&#39;t make that stuff up, although my father apparently can.) It was in a terrible part of town: a poor residential area with no businesses around it. The venture turned out to be a complete failure. What did my father do? He turned it into a bar. Yep. My previously alcoholic father... owns a bar.</p>

<p>There is a lot of stress that comes with running multiple businesses, half of which are constantly failing (seriously. bars do not work unless you, oh, also own a club and sell some ecstacy on the side. do not buy one.) This caused a rift in the marriage of my parents. After a dive in their relationship, my father left my mother for a woman he met at his own bar. I was 9 years old when I learned the ultimately political nature of human relationships. It would not sink in until much later how unfair it was that my father got the house and my mother got me and the bar to live in. Yet, that is how it ended up. This is how I ended up living above a bar, a far less glamourous idea than many of you might be thinking.</p>
<h2 id='berets__waitresses__and_hockey_players'>Berets, Waitresses, and Hockey Players</h2>
<p>In the West End Saloon, I am thankful to have met a wide variety of people. I swept the floors as they drank. I washed their glasses when they were done. They would see my inability to judge and tell me their stories. They would see my youth and note caution with their fates.</p>

<p>An old man in a beret who never spoke a word. He sat alone. A waitress struggling on her own to raise a child. A mill worker named Shadow who cannot get out of his job. He eagerly cautions me about not making the same mistakes. A minor league hockey player who strives for his big break only manages to break his last ten on a beer. A martial artist whose daughter was murdered found it compelled to teach me weekly, but only skills related to self-defense. He had lost the will to fight. I look back, I can see their impact on my life. I love them.</p>

<p>The people from the hills, who look down upon us all, wandered in from time to time. You get a strong sense of the inequality. These people had no idea what plagued this part of town. They could not empathize with individuals who are hopelessly trapped in a job they cannot afford to leave, even though they can barely afford to live. Some people just did not seem to have the issues and concerns of the community that surrounded me. I wondered why.</p>

<p>Yet, I stayed happy. I stayed sane. I owe it to a girl: the janitor&#39;s daughter. She and I would escape into fantasy. We would make up stories where we could fix the world. Stories where we could divert natural disasters. Where we could save people in need. Distractions from the poverty, drugs, drunks, stabbings, and shootings. I foolishly promised her mother that I would protect her, knowing that she would protect me.</p>

<p>But you cannot protect everybody. There is always a day when you have to leave them to fend for themselves. I was 10 years old when I moved out of the bar. There were days later where I needed her strength, and it was not there. It made me wonder if she ever needed mine, and I was not there to help. It bothers me to this day. But, I owe something to her. She taught me the world is malleable. I could indeed use my imagination to fix the things that are wrong.</p>
<h2 id='zero_tolerance'>Zero Tolerance</h2>
<p>My mother, her boyfriend, and I moved to a mill town called Sebewaing in Michigan. We moved into a small little house on an island off of Lake Huron. Again, it is not as glamourous as it sounds.</p>

<p>We moved half-way through the school year, and while I was in elementary school in Pennsylvania, different starting grades meant I was in middle-school in Michigan. It was an abrupt change in my life. Everybody was much older and my classmates were already accustomed to the harsh environment of grades 5 through 8. In a town of only 2,000 one&#39;s personal life could be a weapon. So by accustomed, I mean hiding in plain sight.</p>

<p>My parents, having taken such a passive role in raising me, never explained cultural assumptions such as gender, sex, and preference to me. When I was young, I never understood the division of people into the two lines for recess: boys and girls. Never could I understand why dresses put you in one line and short hair put you in another. Although having and being alone with female friends demonstrated alternative anatomy, I was not prepared for the general assumption that anatomy was tied to gender. I was 11 when I was taught that girls have vaginas and boys have penises. I fought with that idea for a while. I&#39;m glad I did.</p>

<p>When I hit puberty and my libido developed, I found myself attracted to boys and girls. I had no idea that this was culturally shunned. Gender just is not important in who I wanted to spend my private time with. In 6th grade, I found myself in my male friend&#39;s bed. Nothing explicit could really happen. We never discussed it openly. We were afraid. Let me explain, because it is not completely apparent to all. The world is harsh. The world is violent. At that age, in that type of environment, nobody can find out about this. That&#39;s what I learned in middle school. And I suppose I learned some algebra.</p>

<p>I was beaten by the others in the school. I was called names. The feminine mannerisms I developed by having female friends condemned me. My small stature certainly did not help. They asserted themselves in order to be ahead of me. So that it was me and not them. I was beaten for looking at someone&#39;s girlfriend, a friend of mine, the wrong way. I was beaten for just standing around. When this is what you expect from people, you are not exactly loose-lipped about how different you are compared to everybody else. Thanks to zero tolerance rules, I was penalized often. In one case, a boy cornered me and pinned me against the wall. I stabbed him with a pencil (not a deep wound, honestly) in my attempt to get away. Our punishment was detention together in an unsupervised room. My punishment also included forced psychriatric appointments.</p>

<p>At home, it was no better. We had little money and sometimes food was hard to get. My mother went through one abusive relationship after another. I was assaulted there as well. In one case, one was brought up on domestic abuse charges and got 24 hours time served and 20 hours community service. I figured hitting my mother was worth more, but alas, that is not how the world works. But by a combination of going through garbage for recyclables and sharing meals with friends, I made it through ok.</p>

<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/who-am-i/sailboats.jpg' title='' alt='An optimistic artist's rendition of the Bay that spat out Madonna' /><br /><div class='caption'>An optimistic artist's rendition of the Bay that spat out Madonna</div></div><p></p>

<p>It was not long until we were being threatened by her first boyfriend that my mother and I had to move to Bay City out of fear. I slept with a knife under my pillow. I moved to yet another school. I decided to be popular instead of a pincushion and sat at the popular table. I cracked a few jokes and quickly realized how fake the world really is. It all felt wrong. I was not at all comfortable. I moved back to Johnstown for high school, but ultimately I didn&#39;t feel comfortable until college. This seems to be rather typical.</p>
<h2 id='why_i_code'>Why I Code</h2>
<p>Throughout this entire period, I pursued the love for code. For years it was an escape. The machine does what I tell it to do. Its mistakes were really mine. The power of computation is something that I realized everybody could use: the people of this world that are different. The individuals that want to improve their lives and their communities. The reality is that the majority of people on this planet are at a disadvantage. We indeed have the power to fix that.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>It seems like your heart is in it, and that&#39;s all that matters.
<div class="citation">&mdash; <cite>Frans Kaashoek, personal conversation, 2011</cite></div></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I write code because I am aware of adversity and the lack of diversity. Understand that I had it good. I really did. I believe that by utilizing code, and with the immense help of others, we can curb any societal disadvantages. We can, for instance, free information such that education is available at little cost to all of the world. We can build what I call sustainable operating systems where computation is provided to all without the need for centralized maintenance. I will later attempt to describe how these systems work from the perspective of my specialization: software systems.</p>

<p>That&#39;s where each and every one of you come in. Obviously, I can&#39;t build these myself. All of your skills, regardless of ability, regardless of who you are or what people say of you, regardless of who I am and what I can do, can aid in the creation of a world where technology allows an evolution of society. Where my expertise fails, somebody else must contribute. I cannot build these within the bounds of the institutions, academic or otherwise, that exist. These aren&#39;t products; they are environments that provide technology as a healthy lifestyle. So, I will devote all of my energy to defining these systems and implementing them on my own if necessary. I will devote my time to this because I feel I must. I hope you will help me.</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/who-am-i</guid></item><item><title>tmux Configuration for Great Good</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/tmux-configuration-for-great-good</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The tmux (terminal multiplexor) tool is a great way to manage the hellspawn of
computational evolution and TERMINFO hurdling that is the <em>modern</em> terminal. If
you spawn multiple terminals, or even multiple terminal tabs, to manage your
terminal space... stop that immediately.</p>

<p>I just want to jot down some quick configuration fu to set up a decent tmux environment.
We want one with 256 color support, a more than decent amount of scrollback, utf8, etc.</p>
<h2 id='_bash_profile'>.bash_profile</h2>
<p>To have 256 colors, we need to set the TERM variable to xterm-256color by adding an
export to our bashrc. Put this line at the end:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>export TERM=xterm-256color
</code></pre>
<p>Alternatively, (if you don&#39;t want to do that for some reason) we can just alias the tmux command
to set that variable only for tmux:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>alias tmux='TERM=xterm-256color tmux'
</code></pre>
<p>Now, to support 256 colors <strong>within</strong> tmux, we add the following line to the end
of our bashrc:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'># for tmux: export 256color
[ -n &quot;$TMUX&quot; ] &amp;&amp; export TERM=screen-256color
</code></pre><h2 id='_tmux_conf'>.tmux.conf</h2>
<p>Throw whatever subset of these features you&#39;d like into the .tmux.conf file in your
home folder. Create one if it doesn&#39;t exist.</p>
<h3 id='256_colors'>256 Colors</h3><pre><code class='lang-'>set -g default-terminal &quot;screen-256color&quot;
</code></pre><h3 id='scrollback_history'>Scrollback History</h3><pre><code class='lang-'>set -g history-limit 30000   # 30,000 lines of scrollback
</code></pre><h3 id='utf8'>UTF8</h3><pre><code class='lang-'>set -g utf8 on               # utf8
</code></pre><h3 id='mouse'>Mouse</h3><pre><code class='lang-'>setw -g mode-mouse on        # Mouse useful in copy-mode
set  -g mouse-select-pane on # Mouse can select the current pane
</code></pre><h3 id='vi_style_commands'>Vi-Style Commands</h3><pre><code class='lang-'>setw -g mode-keys vi         # vi-style commands in copy-mode
</code></pre><h3 id='ui_color_scheme'>UI Color Scheme</h3>
<p></p><div class='image'><img src='/images/tmux-configuration-for-great-good/256-color-palette.png' title='' alt='256-color terminal palette' /><br /><div class='caption'>256-color terminal palette</div></div><p></p>

<p>While refering to the palette above, set each of these
values to something you find appealing but not distracting. Here
is an example using greens and grays you can add to your .tmux.conf:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'># statusbar colors
set -g status-fg colour236
set -g status-bg colour70

# active window title on statusbar
set-window-option -g window-status-current-fg colour192
set-window-option -g window-status-current-bg default

# inactive window title on statusbar
set-window-option -g window-status-fg colour236
set-window-option -g window-status-bg default

# border around window
set-window-option -g pane-border-fg colour236
set-window-option -g pane-active-border-fg colour70
</code></pre><h2 id='loading_the_configuration'>Loading the configuration</h2>
<p>You do not need to quit tmux to alter the configuration. Just detach and type</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>tmux source ~/.tmux.conf
</code></pre>
<p>And then reattach:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>tmux attach
</code></pre>
<p>And you&#39;re all set.</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/tmux-configuration-for-great-good</guid></item><item><title>Traditional Mistakes in C Programming</title><link>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/traditional-mistakes-in-c-programming</link><description><![CDATA[<p>When you approach a procedural language from an object-oriented, (mostly) type-safe language such as Java, there are certain concepts that do not make the best translation. Of course, the main topic is that of pointers. Frankly, the memory model being exposed to you, unlike the memory abstractions of Java, is a daunting thing at first. It does not have to be!</p>
<h2 id='pointers_in_java'>Pointers in Java</h2>
<p>In Java, we have pointers. In the Java world, they are called references. However, they come with rules that stem from their role as referrers for <em>objects</em>. Since there exists a relationship among objects, the compiler can enforce rules that govern how such a pointer may be used or dereferenced. For instance, you cannot (typically) use a Scanner reference as though it were a FileReader reference. Such a thing would be disastrous as much as it is useless! If there is an is-a relationship created via inheritance, then such a pointer cast is possible. A BufferedFileReader can be used as a FileReader, for instance.</p>
<h2 id='breaking_the_rules'>Breaking the Rules</h2>
<p>In Java, however, it is not completely safe. You can cast to Object and back. Why? Because, under a non-strict compilation, you can cast <strong>to Object</strong> and you can essentially treat any object as any other. Ponder about the implications and object tree that is built from this. Ouch. Java has since created <strong>generics</strong> to get around the need for such an exception. C on the other hand is fundamentally designed to work this way. Why? Because C is a systems language, it runs natively, and it is meant to manipulate the underlying memory model directly (no abstractions, no garbage collector, no virtual machine.)</p>
<h2 id='memory_model'>Memory Model</h2>
<p>So, what is the underlying memory model? It&#39;s an array of bytes starting from 0x00000000 and going as far up as 0xFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF on some systems. Each byte has an address, which is simply a number within the acceptable range of the machine. On a 32-bit addressable machine, that number is 32 bits wide, etc. Within this space are regions of memory dedicated to particular tasks. The regions that are common in an average program are the <strong>code-space</strong>, <strong>data-space</strong>, <strong>readonly-space</strong>, <strong>stack-space</strong>, and <strong>heap-space</strong>. There is also usually nothing allocated at 0x00000000 (NULL) so that using NULL will crash the program with an access violation.</p>

<p>The code-space is for code; data-space is for writable, preallocated data for the program; readonly-space as for read-only, preallocated data for the program; stack-space is the region designated for the stack; heap-space is designated for dynamic allocations. Now, the stack and heap are not preallocated, and as such can grow to any size. A common way to mitigate the two colliding is to virtualize the address space and have the stack grow down and the heap grow up.</p>

<p>Now, in C, you can manipulate both regions. To use the stack, just allocate variables. They will be placed on the activation frame, and thus be placed upon the stack. So, just as an example:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>int x;
</code></pre>
<p>This will place x in the stack frame for the function. This means it will be different for concurrent or consecutive calls of the function.</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>static int x;
</code></pre>
<p>This will place x in the data region, meaning it is shared by all calls of the function.</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>struct node new_node;
</code></pre>
<p>If you define a struct, it will be on the stack as well. This means, once the function returns, the contents of the struct <strong>are destroyed</strong>.</p>
<h2 id='mistake__1___using_a_dangling_pointer'>Mistake #1 - Using a dangling pointer</h2>
<p>Ok. You have a pointer. You know it should point to some... stuff.</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>char* str;
strcpy(str, &quot;Hello World&quot;);
</code></pre>
<p>Pointers are just variables, much like ints, shorts, or doubles. They store a particular value. Much like a reference in Java, they can be declared, yet not be useful. That is, they can point (refer) to nothing (null / NULL). When you declare a variable, it receives an undefined value in C. So, technically, the pointer above points... somewhere. It might point to your code. Or to a valid string elsewhere. Or absolutely, positively, freaking, nothing!</p>

<p>The strcpy function, much like any function that expects some data or a place to put data, expects that the pointer it receives actually refers to a buffer large enough to do the job at hand. It <strong>cannot</strong> allocate anything for you the way it stands. Why? Well, look at the strcpy function:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>char* strcpy(char *dest, const char *source) {
  while(*source != '\0') {
    *dest = *source;
    source++;
    dest++;
  }
  *dest = '\0';
  return dest;
}
</code></pre>
<p>It takes a char pointer. Now, you pass it absolute garbage in the code above that calls strcpy, right? So, even if it wanted to, say, ignore the value you gave it and allocate it itself... it cannot tell you what that pointer is. It could return it, but that defeats the point of passing it in the first place. Typically, the responsibility to free allocated data is done in the same scope as the allocation itself. A function should never allocate for you and require you to explicitly delete it. Since the function requests a pointer, it expects the reference to be valid.</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>char* str = (char*)malloc(12);
strcpy(str, &quot;Hello World&quot;);
free(str);
</code></pre><h2 id='mistake__2___using_a_stack_allocated_struct_to_change_a_global_data_structure'>Mistake #2 - Using a stack-allocated struct to change a global data structure</h2><pre><code class='lang-c'>struct node* head;

void* my_bestfit_malloc(size_t amount) {
  if (head == NULL) {
    head = sbrk(amount + sizeof(struct node));

    // initialize head

    return head + 1;
  }

  // find best fit
  struct node best;
  best = *head;

  while (best.next != NULL) {
    // check best
    best = *best.next;
  }

  // update best
  best.free = 0;
  return (void*)best.next - best.size;
}
</code></pre>
<p>No no no no no! :) Here, the code has done a <strong>deep copy</strong> of the data in the data structure. This is good when you want to copy the data and preserve it before destroying the data in the global data structure. However, if you mutate the data in the copy, it will obviously not persist in the real thing. In this case, the highlighted line (best.free = 0;) will update the local copy and set it to allocated. The data structure itself will not see that. It might allocate this space again, which is pretty terrible!</p>

<p>What you want here is a <strong>shallow copy</strong> of the data. That is, don&#39;t copy the data... copy the value that indicates where the data lives. Which, of course, is a pointer. Always refer to the data via indirection so that when you mutate it, it updates both the copy you are reading and the global data structure at the same time. There is no excuse for this mistake. If you are doing this to avoid the -> syntax, I empathize, but that notation is common and should be used.</p>
<h2 id='mistake__3___pointer_arithmetic'>Mistake #3 - Pointer Arithmetic</h2>
<p>Ok. Pointer math is weird. Enough said.</p>

<p>Well, let&#39;s go over it. It&#39;s weird not difficult. A char* is a pointer to a character, which is a single byte. Pointer arithmetic is when I take a pointer variable and add an integer to it. For instance:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>char* a = &quot;hey&quot;;
char* foo = a;
foo = foo + 2;
printf(&quot;%c\n&quot;, *foo);
</code></pre>
<p>Alright. As you might expect, this will print out &quot;y&quot; on a line. Why? A string is an array of characters. An array is simply a pointer. foo initially points to the first character of the string (&#39;h&#39;). foo contains the address of that character in memory. For instance, it is probably something huge like 0x12345678 or something, which means it is the 305,419,896th byte in the memory space... that&#39;s not incredibly important. What is important is that it is just a number, like the one on my mailbox or the number on your house or apartment, that tells the machine where data should eventually go. Let&#39;s assume foo contains the value 56, so that the string starts at byte 56 in memory.</p>

<p>When I add 2 to foo, I push the address further in the address space. 56 becomes 58. Because the string is stored contiguously in memory, we are now looking at the third character in the string. Neat. Direct manipulation of memory is really powerful. It gives you full range of the memory space. That is, it is horribly unsafe. Which means... we can do things like the following:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>char* a = &quot;hey&quot;;
char* b = &quot;you&quot;;
char* foo = a;
foo = foo + 5;
printf(&quot;%c\n&quot;, *foo);
</code></pre>
<p>You might be surprised to learn that this will (generally) print out &#39;o&#39; on a line. Whaaaaa?!?! Actually, it is quite simple. The strings are allocated one after another. So memory looks like this:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>[ h][ e][ y][\0][ y][ o][ u][\0]
 56  57  58  59  60  61  62  63
</code></pre>
<p>The second line is the address associated to these bytes. As you can see, 56+2 indeed points to a &#39;y&#39; character. And, sure enough, 56 + 5, or 61, points to an &#39;o&#39; character. As you can see, pointers directly map to the underlying memory. They lose all association to their original data structure. They are just numbers. Pretty tame, and extremely simple.</p>

<p>To aid programmers, the designers of C decided that pointer math is special. Why would anyone want to address something within an int? or within a struct? You wouldn&#39;t generally need to do this. So, when an integer is added to a pointer, the address is incremented in steps of the size of the type the pointer refers. Let&#39;s just look at examples:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>char* foo = 56; foo + 1;        // foo == 57
short* foo = 56; foo + 1;       // foo == 58 assuming shorts are 2 bytes
int* foo = 56; foo + 1;         // foo == 60 assuming ints are 4 bytes
struct node* foo = 56; foo + 1; // foo == 56 + sizeof(node)
</code></pre>
<p>Interesting. And confusing. And prone to error. But, ultimately more useful than simply adding to the address itself, right? So, it makes sense.</p>

<p>In the malloc assignment, it is bad to do this:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>struct node* foo = sbrk(sizeof(node) + size);
return foo + sizeof(node);
</code></pre>
<p>Good to do this:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>return (char*)foo + sizeof(node);
</code></pre>
<p>Or this:</p>
<pre><code class='lang-'>return foo + 1;
</code></pre><h2 id='style'>Style</h2>
<p>Pft. Style? How can style be a legitimate programming issue? Because reading code is the most important facet of programming. If your code is not legible, your code is next to worthless.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Programs must be written for people to read, and only incidentally for machines to execute.</p>

<div class="citation">&mdash; <cite>Abelson & Sussman</cite>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Structure-Interpretation-Computer-Programs-Engineering/dp/0262011530/sr=8-1/qid=1163785017?ie=UTF8&s=books">Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</a></div>
</blockquote>

<p>That pretty much sums it up. Programs are for people. I mean, that&#39;s the entire point of a programming language, after all. Just as it is with a natural language, such as English, there are conventions that, when used, make the writing easier to consume. You have all read different writing styles, and understand that certain styles appeal to you more than others. In the programming world, just as the literary world, these styles are debated. One thing is true: by sticking to the correct convention for your audience, you are more easily understood.</p>

<p>That said, each language has its own standard for conventions. This has to do with tab spacing, hard or soft tabs, function naming, brace position, file structure... you name it. In Java, for instance, functions are written in <strong>camelCase</strong>, while classes are named in the uppercase variant or <strong>UpperCamelCase</strong> (aka <strong>PascalCase</strong>). Constants are in <strong>ALLCAPS</strong>. Typically these conventions are not defined as part of the language. That is, the parser (technically the lexer) does not look for, treat differently, or cause an error when these conventions go unused. Other languages, such as Ruby, give these conventions semantic meaning. For instance, defining a variable name in all caps will create a constant.</p>

<p>C works like Java (Java is, after all, a <strong>C-family language</strong>... ok fine... they are both <strong>Algol-family</strong> for you programming-language-smartypants out there.) That is, the conventions are not enforced by the language, they are social. That said, after 40 years, the conventions are very rigid and surprisingly common. This is a testament to how necessary they truly are.</p>
<ul><li><strong>Function names</strong>: void these_lowercase_things_have_underscores(int a, int b, int c, void *p) { }
</li><li><strong>Constants</strong>: ALL_CAPITAL_LETTERS
</li><li><strong>Tabs</strong>: There isn&#39;t a preference. Hard or soft (that is, just using spaces instead). Spaces are generally more consistent, and your editors can generally emit them when you press &#39;tab&#39;.
</li><li><strong>Tab Size</strong>: nowadays 2 or 4 spaces.
</li></ul><h2 id='mistake__4___dropping_void_off_of_functions'>Mistake #4 - Dropping void off of functions</h2>
<p>ALWAYS put the void before a function that returns nothing. It has meaning. For the same reason an implied subject is weird in English writing... don&#39;t drop nouns in your programs. In fact, by not putting void in front, it&#39;s actually a function that returns int. So, now you have an int-function that has no return. Eww! Always specify the return type; enough said. :)</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>/* A */ void f(void);
/* B */ f(void);

/* A and B have VASTLY different return types! */
</code></pre><h2 id='mistake__5___wrong_conventions_for_functions'>Mistake #5 - Wrong conventions for functions</h2>
<p>Why is myBestFitMalloc() confusing when you expect to see a C function call? Because that does not look like a C function call. So, the code does not flow very well when you are trying to read through it. It does not register as a function call immediately. That slows everything down. If you use a library that names its functions a different way than you, your code will look fairly ugly due to the inconsistency. Another good reason to commit to the <em>standard conventions</em>. Guess what... everybody conforms to this out in the wild. Lowercase with underscore delimiters. It may not look good to you, but it looks beautiful to everybody else.</p>
<h2 id='mistake__6___indentation'>Mistake #6 - Indentation</h2>
<p>Why is this important? Because of how nice it is to quickly identify scope. I generally read code and know that a variable declared in a certain column will be alive as long as the indentation is at least that wide. I know where a while loop begins and ends just by skimming. If you misplace one tab or space, your code becomes drastically harder to read. Also, ensure that your brackets are always positioned the same way. If you put them on the same line as the <strong>if</strong>, then do that always. Overall, consistency is what matters. It is so important, that there is a standard UNIX program (indent) that will correct and switch indentation styles.</p>

<p>So, by all means, decide among yourselves whether you will choose tabs or spaces, <strong>vim</strong> or emacs, <a  href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indent_style' title=''>K&amp;R or Allman</a> (K&amp;R K&amp;R <strong>K&amp;R!!!</strong>). If you choose <em>Whitesmiths</em>... I... I just can&#39;t save you.</p>
<h2 id='mistake__7___functions_that_do_not_take_arguments'>Mistake #7 - Functions that do not take arguments</h2>
<p>People really do not understand this, and you see this often.</p>
<pre><code class='lang-c'>/* A */ void f();
/* B */ void f(void);
</code></pre>
<p>I do not blame you. In C++ or Java, (A) would be the correct choice to describe a function that has no arguments. However, in C, it is actually choice (B). Why? Because (A) is a function that takes any number of arguments. So, if you used (A) in C, you could call it with foo(2, 4, &quot;hello&quot;) and it would fire and maybe this has consequences you do not expect. Therefore, you use construction (B). I will <em>not see any of you make this mistake</em>. Resist the temptation, and you are now better than 80% of all C programmers ever. :)</p>
<h2 id='mistake__8___the_one_letter_variable_name'>Mistake #8 - The one-letter variable name</h2>
<p>Hey! HEY! Do not use one-letter variable names. Names are there for you. The human being in front of the keyboard. The computer throws them away. So, why make them so cryptic? It&#39;s only acceptable in certain conventional places, like using &#39;i&#39; for a loop counter. (Even then, that&#39;s weird. Because some people use &#39;i&#39; as a pure counter and <em>not as an index</em>. Confusing.)</p>
<h2 id='mistake__9___the_all_powerful_function'>Mistake #9 - The all powerful function</h2>
<p>Congratulations on reading this far. This part is about a common problem a lot of new programmers face: the megalomanical function. It&#39;s a function that believes it is an infallible god that was created to do all. It cooks AND cleans. It accelerates AND brakes. It grows the plants, sows the fields, and harvests the produce at the end of the season. Here&#39;s the thing... functions should do <strong>one</strong> thing. Absolutely nothing more. That&#39;s its purpose: to provide <strong>a</strong> function. The technical term for what a function does is its <strong>behavior</strong>. Isn&#39;t it hard enough to get it to behave in one particular way, let alone many?</p>

<p>When a function does just one thing, it is easier to write, easier to understand, easier to maintain, easier to throw away and start over (<strong>refactor</strong>), easier to debug, and easier to test manually or write automated tests (<strong>specifications</strong>) to ensure its correctness.</p>

<p>How do you detect a runaway, malevolent function? You can... smell it. You can tell when something... smells a little fishy. So, look for <strong>code smells</strong>! (Yes... that&#39;s the technical term. I didn&#39;t invent it; don&#39;t look at me that way.)</p>
<ol><li><p><strong>Variable declarations halfway down a function</strong></p>

<p>You know that code you write where you do something and then you declare a bunch of new things about halfway through a function body? Yeah. Don&#39;t do that. Why? It&#39;s a <em>smell</em>. It says &quot;Hey. I&#39;m switching jobs here... putting on this new hat.&quot; That means you have written two functions and given it the same name and put it in the same body. Have you ever seen Siamese twins where one wanted to go into show business but the other was camera shy? Not. Good. People.</p>
</li><li><p><strong>Many returns</strong></p>

<p>When you have many exits for your little function highway, it can seem extremely useful. And, sure, it is useful. This function gleefully reacts to many different situations and conditionally responds to many different stimuli. But, in the end, this can be an indication that this function is doing <strong>far far</strong> too much. Think about drawing your function out as a flow chart. It should really be able to fit neatly on a small piece of paper and roughly be linear. If it is not... well, draw it out anyway. What are you looking for? Small isolated pockets of activity. These pockets should have been functions... and now you can pull them out and simply call them appropriately. It could very well be that each return in your original function represents a separate behavior and therefore should just be its own function.</p>

<p>As my grandmother used to say, &quot;One function too many is better than one function too mangy.&quot;</p>
</li><li><p><strong>Finding yourself adding something within a function</strong></p>

<p>You know that thing that isn&#39;t broken? What do you do with that thing... oh right. You <strong>don&#39;t fix it</strong>. If you are ever like... &quot;this function should do more,&quot; lick a battery and stop yourself from believing that&#39;s true. That function is <strong>just fine</strong>. What you want is a new function to perform that new behavior. If that means breaking up the function you have into two pieces... so be it. If you can&#39;t add the behavior you want without breaking a function up... then that function <em>needed</em> to be broken apart. Let&#39;s not create big functions. If we make too many of them, they might lobby Congress to be considered people.</p>

<p>There are other smells, for instance the trivial &quot;It doesn&#39;t fit on a single page in my text editor,&quot; but generally it&#39;s obvious when you&#39;ve gone <strong>too far</strong>.</p>
</li></ol>
<p>As you can see. Style is serious business. It is why there are points for it on the assignments, and it is why I&#39;m so critical about it. It&#39;s for your own good! :)</p>

<p>Happy Hacking,
wilkie</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://blog.davewilkinsonii.com/posts/traditional-mistakes-in-c-programming</guid></item></channel></rss>